<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letters between the Ld George Digby, and Sr Kenelm Digby kt. concerning religion.</title>
            <author>Bristol, George Digby, Earl of, 1612-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 191 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1355_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209464</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868346</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868346</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169831</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77522)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169831)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 178:E1355[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Letters between the Ld George Digby, and Sr Kenelm Digby kt. concerning religion.</title>
                  <author>Bristol, George Digby, Earl of, 1612-1677.</author>
                  <author>Digby, Kenelm, Sir, 1603-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 132 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Moseley, and are to be sold at his shop, at the sign of the Prince's Arms in St Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In this edition the last page is dated: March 30. 1639.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 26 1650"; the 51 in the date has been crossed through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christianity --  Essence, genius, nature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169831:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LETTERS BETWEEN The L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>GEORGE DIGBY,</hi> AND <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> KENELM DIGBY</hi> k<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, CONCERNING Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the ſign of the <hi>Prince's Arms</hi> in St <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:169831:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169831:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is no <hi>EXCUSE</hi> (though too often it is made one) to tell Thee theſe <hi>LETTERS</hi> are now made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick to prevent falſe Copies: for really, if you have not theſe, you will be abus'd with others, ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect
<pb facs="tcp:169831:3"/>and mangled, that we may justly pronounce them to be none of the Authors own. In Matters of <hi>Religion</hi> there ought to be greateſt care to publiſh nothing but what is genuine, which here (without more words) thou wilt ſoon find is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully offered thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169831:3"/>
            <head>LETTERS BETWEEN The L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>GEORGE DIGBY</hi> AND S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>KENELM DIGBY</hi> k<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, CONCERNING RELIGION.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>My nobleſt Couſin and deareſt friend.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Ever thought my ſelf a Rich man in the many teſtimonies of your favour, being perſwaded that the authority of your eſteeming me, may work more upon the World to my advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, then many perſonall defects of mine own to my prejudice. Among my beſt titles to valuation with Worthy men, I treaſure up your laſt Letter, expecting to receive there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by as much Credit hereafter, as I doe now obligation; when thoſe that finde it, (knowing your eminence and only my name) ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169831:4"/>miſconceive my praiſes there to have bin of your judgement, which I muſt refer meerly to your love and civility. Perſiſt I beſeech you in the former of theſe, and reſtrain your ſelf in the exceſs of the latter, permitting and owning me to be your friend, without making me mine own flatterer; of which I can never come in danger, but by your Commendations. I think my ſelf as happy to bear the name of your friend, and promiſe to my ſelf as much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie by the relation, as he who ingraved Sir <hi>Philip Sydnie</hi>'s friendſhip on his Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>But I muſt tell you, I aſpire yet to a farr greater felicity, that is, to be made worthy of ſo brave an appellation, to which you can beſt contribute, if you pleaſe to impart freely to me your own rare abilities, and my weakneſſes, rather then to darken theſe unto me, in exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing but the ſlighteſt part that you excell in, Courtlineſs. To take you off from this, and to engage you in the other, give me leave to lay hold on that part of your Letter which concerns my Studies. Wherein, as your exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and advice have ever been my prime di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory in the way of them, ſo in the ſeverall judgements of what I read, yours muſt be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with me of ſingular Authority:</p>
               <p>Yet in the particular concerning the Fathers, I muſt confeſs, as I came unto them, perhaps
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169831:4"/>with different preparations, ſo I have likewiſe peruſed many of them with reflections upon their uſefulneſs, far differing from thoſe you ſpecifie. I am ſo farr from receiving them as Judges, that in many caſes I cannot admit them as witneſſes Authentick enough, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to paſs a Verdict in Religion. I diſcover me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks too prone a byas in moſt of their evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, either to the eſtabliſhing of their own private opinions, or to the deſtruction of their adverſaries. And this even in the moſt Primitive of them faction it ſeems, and a kinde of Sectary paſſion, having had as ſtrong, though not ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a Current, even neer to the very ſprings of verity, as afterward in the remoter Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, as you can much better inſtance (if you pleaſe) then I, out of <hi>Euſebius, Epiphanius,</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Auguſtin;</hi> who themſelves alſo, as they ſeem to adhere to the Catholick Church, and as the <hi>Roman</hi> glories in them, may well be by both ſides allowed an Expurgator.</p>
               <p>For that which you ſay, Secondly, that you rely more upon the Fathers, for what they tell us they were taught, then upon what they teach, I profeſs I ſhould do ſo too, could I be but half ſo well aſſured of the firſt part of your reaſon; namely, that the former was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from an infallible Authority, as I am of the other, that their own reaſons were liable to Error. But to tell you true, as I can yet finde
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169831:5"/>no reaſon to make me acknowledge that there is any infallible Authority, but only the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (which I conceive is not that you mean;) ſo do I finde as little that the Fathers (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe before the firſt <hi>Nicene</hi> Councell) were perſwaded of any ſuch. And grant they were, I can leaſt of all diſcern which of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious doctrins they deliver, were rightly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to them from that unerring authority. Since it is apparent, methinks, that they do teach many uncertainties and errors, as Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matically, and with as ſolemn confirmations, as they do the moſt authentique truths. Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhal you find Scripture alledged more frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by them, or the Church tradition proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med more lowdly in any point of Faith, then by <hi>Juſtin</hi> and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in the rigid cenſure of the uſe of Images, and in the ſame <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> in affirming Chriſts deſcent to free the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarks; and in theſe two, and divers others, the groſs aſſertion of the Angels copulation with women: and laſtly, then in all the <hi>Millenaries</hi> moſt confident authorizing of their <hi>Judaick</hi> doctrine. Theſe are perhaps of the ſlighter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, ſuch as flow eaſieſt into a Letter from a bad memory, and yet I pray you reſolve me which of them I ſhall let paſs, as derived from infallibilitie? whether that which our Church approves, and the <hi>Roman</hi> condemns, as the firſt; or that which the <hi>Roman</hi> agrees to, and we
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169831:5"/>diſallow, as the ſecond; or the ſecond laſt, which both ſides reject? I profeſs I am as yet to diſtinguiſh which of them theſe Fathers meant we ſhould ſwallow as delivered to them, and which chew and conſider as onely delivered by them. Theſe and many more ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcileable paſſages in them, have rendred me much alike affected both to what you ſay they tell us they were taught, and to what they teach; that is, to have my reaſon, as much as I can cleared and enlightened by both, but to ſuffer it to be hoodwinkt and lead implicitly by neither. I reverence thoſe holy Fathers, as divine eſtabliſhers of Faith in things where they all concur, and where not, as happy aides of the underſtanding, and as it were ſacred bellowes of the ſoul whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make it glow unto contrition, and fervor of zeal, or to ſubtilize and exalt it into flames of contemplation.</p>
               <p>It is now high time for me to beg your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, for having licenſed my ſelf ſo much to your trouble. It is an inconvenience drawn up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you by your exceſs of favour and obliging<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that have incouraged me freely to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs to your ſelf my ill-digeſted opinions; wherein toward any other I ſhould have been reſtrained by ſhame and the conſciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mine own incapacities, but from you I ever promiſe my ſelf rectifying, where
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169831:6"/>from another I might look for contempt: All your juſt cenſures, I am ſure will be ſweetened inſtantly by this one conſideration, that this pennance hath been laid upon you by</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Nobleſt Couſin,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your faithfull Servant</signed>
                  <dateline>SHERBURN, <date>Novemb. 2. 1638.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>G. D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Nobleſt Lord, and moſt honoured Friend;</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY unſteady abode in the town, and frequent ſuddain excurſions out of it of late, have caſt me ſo far behinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with your Lordſhip, not onely for what civility requireth of me, but for what duty bindeth me unto, as I was grown to a belief that I could make no other amends for my long ſilence, but by coming on purpoſe to <hi>Sherburn</hi> to you to excuſe it. And therefore out of an ill baſhfulneſs I forbore acknowledging my fault by Letter, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring that till I was in ſtate to repair it by mine own perſonal attendance. But that being not likely to fall out ſo ſoon, I being to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169831:6"/>go to morrow to my Mothers, and thence to my own houſe for ſome weekes; and I having lately received a picture from my Lord <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> with command to ſend it as ſoon as I could to your Lordſhip, I durſt not make that a priſoner till I got liberty my ſelfe to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you. By which means I am engaged, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being able to defer it any longer, to give you humble thanks for your letter of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>November,</hi> and to crave your pardon that I came thus late to doe it. So ſudden and diſtracted an houre as I have now to write in, would deterre me from offering at any return to ſo obliging and judicious a Letter, till I had a greater freedom both of time and thoughts. But I can never be taken unprovided for the firſt part, my ſincere affection to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and ſence of your favours ever out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weighing any other humane object that may buſie my mind: &amp; for the ſecond, of anſwering your judicious objections, I ſhall confide more for the ſolution of them in your owne calme and impartiall reflections upon them, then in ought I ſhall be able to reply. Therefore had I never ſo much time, I would for this intent imploy it onely in reducing the matters into your remembrance, and intreating you to commit the appearances on both ſides fairly one againſt another into the balances, and let your owne Reaſon hold the Scale,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169831:7"/>which I muſt acknowledge with exceſſe of joy, to be the ſtrongeſt and moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere that I know in any man. I ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the performance of this task with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining to your Lordſhip in the Fathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, and repreſenting their grievances to your Lordſhip, that you are ſo rigorous to them, as to exclude them from being wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes in matters of Religion. Their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, as well of underſtanding, as of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, will not let them be troubled when they are recuſed as Judges: They never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce any thing out of their own breaſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which they will confine other mens aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents. But when they tell you plainly what they were taught, and what they ſinde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved and practiſed generally throughout the whole Church, have they not reaſon to take it unkindly to be rejected. If you will examine their veracity by al thoſe circumſtances that are uſually conſidered in taking mens depoſitions, you will find them ſtrong on their ſide. They were right honeſt men, not onely believed, but known to be ſuch by all the world. They are acknowledged on all hands to be ſo judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as would more blemiſh ones owne judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then theirs, but to cal it in queſtion. What they wrote of, are matters belonging to their own Art and Trade, in which ſurely they would have great care and attention not to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169831:7"/>miſtake, ſince their own and their poſterities eternall ſalvation depended on it: Since then there is will and ability to inform us of truth, why ſhould we ſuſpect them? What can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare ſtronger to us in oppoſition of what they deliver as witneſſes, to make us doubt their evidence? and conſequently to brand them with the imputation of falſhood and ignorance, flattering our ſelves that new and clearer lights ſhine to us, and that we know more then they? Their private opinions (for the eſtabliſhing of which your Lordſhip ſaith, you diſcover too prone a Bias in moſt of their evidence) doe not intereſt our beliefs; in ſuch poynts we are as free as they. Nor can I believe ſo ill of any of them, as to make thoſe to paſſe for currant, they would ſtamp upon them the ſeale of being taught from hand to hand, and of tradition from Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and of the generall and uncontrouled beliefe and practiſe of the Church; or if they did, certainly their nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous adverſaries would not have let ſuch foul play ſcape their note. It is true, they were ever, as your Lordſhip obſerves, earneſt and ſevere againſt them who were ſuch, as if they had been mild againſt their Hereſies, they would never have gained the name of Fathers and Pillars of the Church, nor have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced as Saints by ſucceeding Ages. The
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169831:8"/>faction and ſectary-paſſion that your Lordſhip remarketh even neer the ſprings of verity, belongeth onely to their adverſaries; their warmth is juſt and due zeale: And for thoſe three Fathers of whom your Lordſhip ſayes, that we as well as you may allow them an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgator; I profeſſe my ſlender reading ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver met, to my beſt remembrance, with any do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of faith in them, that I doe not entirely aſſent unto. In the next place, my Lord, I muſt cleare what I mean by the infallible Authority from whence the Fathers derived what they were taught, which I diſtinguiſhed againſt what of themſelves they teach. Of this later ſort are the reflections that they make upon the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, when in their Comments or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons they deliver to us what occurred to them in the interpretation of the Texts of it. And when they are but barely ſuch, I conceive they are to have no more weight with thoſe that have ability to examine them, then the reaſons wherewith they are accompanied do give them. But the other points of Doctrine I take to have been taught by Chriſt to his Apoſtles, and by them preached through the world, and then again delivered to the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing age by them that had theſe points incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated into their hearts by the Apoſtles, and in this manner with care (and every where) handed over from age to age; which upon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169831:8"/>particular occaſions the Fathers uſed to ſum up and produce againſt Innovators that would make breaches upon the ancient and generally received Faith of the Church. Doctrines thus delivered, I conceive, to be derived from infallible Authority, as well as the Scriptures, and <hi>withall, that it is ſo ſafely conveyed to us, as we are as deeply obliged to beleeve it, as what the Scriptures teach us,</hi> and in governing the tenor of our Faith, to give them much the precedency: Becauſe by ſuch Tradition, we are fully, plainly, and practically taught how to underſtand it, and the buſineſs and errand of it is, to deliver it ſo unto us; whereas the cauſes of writing the particular Books of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, were for other particular ends, and not to give us a compleat body of Faith. And thoſe Articles of it that they do deliver us, are not ſo plainly expreſſed, that every body can under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them. So that if it be once admitted, that by ſuch tradition, there can be had in all ages a compleat and true knowledg of what Chriſt taught, it cannot be denied, but that it is an eaſier and better rule to guide our underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the affairs of Religion, then to reſort for that end to the Scripture alone. And that ſuch tradition is infallible, I have endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to prove in another diſcourſe which your Lordſhip hath, ſo that I will not trouble you here with any repetitions upon that Subject.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169831:9"/>Now when I wrote to your Lordſhip my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the uſe to be made of reading the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, relying upon them more for what they were taught, then for what they teach; it was as taking them for faithful Collectors of the tradition that they found general through the Church in their times, and ſincere conveyers of them to us: And this courſe you ſhall finde even among the ancienteſt of them. When St. <hi>Austin</hi> will eſtabliſh the doctrine of praying for the dead, he telleth that it hath been the practiſe of the whole Church from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time. The like he doth againſt the Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians, and upon ſeveral other occaſions; and directeth us to enquire what faith is profeſſed in the Churches eſtabliſhed by the Apoſtles; from whom he reckoneth on the uninterrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſucceſſion of Paſtors unto his time: And by them he deriveth the preſent Doctrine from the firſt preachers, who had it immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from Chriſt. <hi>Tertullian,</hi> when he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth againſt Hereſie, giveth you a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of the Biſhops of ſeveral Churches, from the ſeveral Apoſtles that planted them; and with the ſucceſſions of the perſons urgeth the ſucceſſion in thoſe Churches of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine he ſeeketh to eſtabliſh. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> doth the like, and generally all of them; which they do not onely when they uſe thoſe formal poſitive words that the whole Church hath
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169831:9"/>received from the Apoſtles, and holdeth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſuch and ſuch a Doctrine: but at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times alſo when they do but intimate it in their diſcourſes, which intimation is ſuch as is eaſily perceptible to whoſoever of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall read them impartially. Therefore to ſummon up as ſhort and as plainly as I can, the uſe, as I conceive is to be made of reading the Fathers; I ſay that letting paſs what they writ as Commentors upon the Scriptures, and as Phlioſophers, and all which is but as Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines and Schollers, we are generally to take hold of what they deliver us as Paſtors of the Church, which appeareth chiefly by what they writ againſt thoſe they brand with Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, which they could not do, were not thoſe points which they cenſure, againſt the known and general tradition of the Church: And next when they deliver us dogmatically and profeſſedly any doctrine, in ſuch ſort as we may reaſonably conceive they intended we ſhould take it as matter of faith, not giving it as conceptions of their own, which they bring onely learned arguments on texts of Scripture to maintain: In all which a free &amp; good judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will eaſily diſcern by reading them, which way to incline; which I knowing your Lordſhip to be, do beſeech you to apply it a little induſtriouſly, to collect throughout their ſenſe, and by what they ſay to frame a model
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169831:10"/>of the Government, Beleif, and practiſe of the Church wherein they lived, and then tell me whether it be like yours or ours: It is worth the while; Criticks labour to get ſome knowledge of the manners and cuſtomes of Ages long ſince paſt by little fragments of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity that have hardly ſcaped into their hands. And Lawyers get a knowledge of the Government and frame of the State in Kings raigns long agoe, by broken and disjoynted Records, that they meet with ſcattered in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Files. And theſe maimed evidences by chance fallen into their Hands, do ſerve to beget a fairer body of knowledge, when they know how to make a right uſe of them, and ſuch as will convince an indifferent and equal hearer: much more certainly the Fathers works that handle profeſſedly and at large the affairs of the Church and Religion, and whereof we have ſuch plenty, will fairly inform a rational and diſcourſing man of the true ſtate of them in their times, and what they conceived and had been taught, imported Heaven or Hell in mans belief and practiſe; which I am ſure your Lordſhip will allow to carry a great ſtroke in ours, and from which it is madneſs, if not impiety, to depart upon leſs grounds then a demonſtration to convince the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Though I have already too much treſpaſſed upon your Lordſhips patience by my tedious
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169831:10"/>Letter, yet I may not conclude it, till I have ſaid a word or two to the foure inſtances your Lordſhip giveth toward the latter end of yours. Firſt, for the uſe of Images, I doe not conceive it to be a precept given by Chriſt, but ſince introduced by the Governors of the Church, as a thing convenient to raiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion in the people.</p>
               <p>Now things of that nature may be convenient at one time, and unfit at another. When I do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry was freſh in the memory and practiſe of the world, it was dangerous to admit it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the primitive times <hi>Juſtin</hi> and <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> might have reaſon to cry it down. But becauſe there was no precept of Chriſt in that behalfe conſerved in the Church, you ſee they urge not the authority of Tradition of the Church to beat down their uſe, but arguments of their own, and Texts of Scripture produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by them; whereas now in times ſecured from that danger, and a great good appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in them (they being as a Father ſaid, the bookes of unlettered perſons to beget know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and ſtirre up devotion in them) as ſtrong arguments, and as pregnant Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are produced for their uſe, and to juſtifie the Governours of the Church in recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them to the people. Your ſecond in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is of <hi>Tertullians</hi> affirming Chriſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent to free the Patriarkes; which I conceive
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169831:11"/>not onely he, but all the Fathers that ever ſpake of that particular, deliver it in a matter of faith, and ſo it hath been ever held by the Church: which word of <hi>Deſcent</hi> I take it is to be underſtood, as we all doe, the Article of the Creed, <hi>He deſcended into Hell,</hi> that is, by his power and operation at leaſt, by which he confounded the damned, comforted the ſoules in Purgatory, and brought to the ſight of God, thoſe in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, that is, a place of reſt, where yet they enjoyed not the beatificall viſion. For to give other moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and place to a ſoule, is a queſtion in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, and concernes not faith; and ſuch was the aſſertion of the Angels copulation with women; for many, or rather moſt of the Fathers were of opinion, that they were not pure Spirits, but had very ſubtile &amp; immortall bodies (the contrary of which was never yet delivered as matter of faith, howbeit by force of Argument now the corporiety of Angels is exploded out of the Schools) and thus ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that opinion, the way is obvious enough in commenting ſome Texts of Scripture, to fall into that error, which ſo becommeth an error in Philoſophy, and in no wiſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning faith. And that other of the Millenaries, which is the laſt your Lordſhip urgeth, appeareth plainly to have growne among ſome of the Fathers, (with whom the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169831:11"/>of <hi>Papias</hi> weighed much) by literally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting a Text of the <hi>Apocalyps;</hi> but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any of them urged the generally received opinion of the Church, nor publick Tradition from Chriſt and the Apoſtles. And beſides, the Church has never yet to this day condemned as an hereſie, that part of the Millenaries be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, which ſome of the Fathers held (which is, of the Saints reigning with Chriſt a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares upon earth after their reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and enjoying onely ſpirituall delights) but only other foule enormities which went under the name of the Millenaries hereſies. Now by what I have ſaid to thoſe inſtances in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and bringing that ſpirit that I ſaid before was required to the reading of the Fathers, I conceive it will be no hard matter to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine which of them, as your Lordſhip ſayes, we are to ſwallow as delivered to them, and which to chaw and conſider as onely delivered by them. One thing more I ſhall adde in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, which is, That a large and great ſoule, like yours, expreſſeth it ſelfe more to its ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in weighing in the powerfull ſcale of reaſon, that it hath the main bulk of what it is to judge of, rather than to dwell with too ſcrupulous a diligence upon little quillets and niceties, which admit arguments on both ſides, and in the mean time let ſlide away unnoted, that great deale which is uncontroulable and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169831:12"/>plaine, as though one were but to declame in Schoole to exerciſe ones wit, and therefore he maketh choyce of ſome ingenious Paradox a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a known and received truth; and to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne it, can bring but againſt the skirts of it arguments or rather cavils of wit, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to grapple with the main body of it, and ſeeks rather to puzzle and embroyle his adverſary, then weightily to eſtabliſh the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid truth. This is a ſubject that is deeply to be conſidered for uſe, (the importanteſt that we can have, not argued upon for oſtentation) and that a wiſe man ought to ſeek a ſettlement in, and not aim at the applauſe of being ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted, by reducing all things to uncertainty. Therefore, good my Lord, apply that great underſtanding you are ſo excellently endowed withall, to build as well as to pull down, and read not the Fathers with a fore-laid deſigne to enerve their authority; but with an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency to yeeld your aſſent to what upon the whole matter you ſhall judge reaſonable for you ſo to doe. And ſince I know that your judgement muſt in all things that are contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted before it, of this nature, tend to a ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment one way or other, (for only ſciolous wits float onely in uncertainty, as delighting to make objections, and raiſe a duſt which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their weak eyes cannot looke through) let me recommend to you not onely to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169831:12"/>whether the opinion you meet with in your reading, repugnant to what you were formerly imbued with, be concludingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated or no, but likewiſe examine as ſtrictly the reaſon you have for your own, and where the ſcale weighes heavieſt, give your aſſent. For ſince of contradictory propoſitions one muſt neceſſarily be true, and the other falſe, a man proceedeth upon ſafe grounds, if he take for a firm truth what is oppoſite to an aſſertion that betrayes its own weakneſſe; whereas if you look onely upon the true, you may happily at the inſtant not finde a full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to every objection that may be raiſed againſt it; which proceedeth not from the weakneſſe of the thing, but from ours, that cannot at the firſt ſight look into the bottome of it.</p>
               <p>You ſee, my Lord, how confident I am with you, to tell you what upon the preſent in ſuch ſhortneſs and diſtraction of time occurreth to me upon this ſubject, which your goodneſſe hath invited me unto, and I begge the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of it, firſt in pardoning me; and next, in imparting to me your reflections upon them, which I profeſſe ſincerely, I value beyond any mans, and moſt of all, in loving me as you have ever done, which is the happieſt condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that can give a bleſſing unto</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>London</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>Decem.</hi> 29. 1638.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
                  <signed>your Lordſhips moſt humble and moſt faithfull ſervant, <hi>K. D.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:169831:13"/>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My deare Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WHen I wrot my Letter, I intended to review and copy it; but it held me much longer time then I deſigned to it. It ſhould not have been with my dull head and hand, an after-ſuppers work, and after comming home from vain entertainment with ſome imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſhe-wits that moſt tyrannically had ſeized upon me: They had tun'd my brains to ſo croſſe a Key, as afterward all ſerious Images came ſo lamely into my fancy, as I may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſend you this rough draught of them, and ſo ſlowly halting, as I was in good faith three houres about thoſe blotted and interli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſheets. For it was an houre paſt midnight afore I had done, which was not one to enter upon ſo tedious a task, as to lick this abortive and miſhapen Embrion into form. And now this morning my company calls upon me to be gone, ſo that I am in a ſtrait to appeare before your Lordſhip, either extreamly negligent if I deferre till my return to towne, the anſwering of your Letter, and the ſending my Lord <hi>Ruſſels</hi> Picture; or extreamly indiſcreet, if I ſend you ſo rude and indigeſted refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions upon your ſo judicious and ſtrong
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169831:13"/>diſcourſe, wherein the inſtances, though your Lordſhip be pleaſed to call them ſlight ones, and ſuch as flow eaſieſt into a Letter from a bad memorie, yet you muſt give me leave to believe them the ſtrongeſt and ſharpeſt that can be urged upon this ſubject, and the flower and Quinteſſence of what Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi> and the beſt wits have produced againſt the tradition of the Church, and the authority of the Fathers. But I will chooſe rather to fall into your hands for the latter, then under your cenſure for the firſt; and ſo asking you a thouſand pardons, I ſend you this, by which, all I can hope, is, that you will at leaſt diſcern in me a great willingnes to come out of your debt in this kinde (for all other I know impoſſible) though I am but a flow and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect paymaſter: and that you will in ſome meaſure, gueſs at what I would ſay if I had time to digeſt and range it as it ſhould be. I ſhall here only by way of ſupplement, adde this more concerning the <hi>Millenaries</hi> (becauſe I would not render my Letters more illegible by new interlining it) that as I remember <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> himſelf, ſaith it is an opinion not generally beleeved in the Church, but that many of the Orthodox reject it; howbeit he profeſſeth to hold it for true, and accordingly endeavoureth to prove it by authority of Scripture; all which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169831:14"/>manifeſtly declareth, that it was no avowed tradition of the Church from Chriſt; it is true, <hi>Papias</hi> ſeemeth to intimate as though it were in ſome obſcure manner derived from Chriſt, but not as a thing commanded to be preached and taught. He telleth it as a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie or ſecret, whiſpered by him to ſome of the Apoſtles, whom he would oblige more then their fellowes, by imparting ſome thing to them for their knowledge, that the reſt ſhould be ignorant of. But no ſuch by-rivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let (though it ſhould come from the true foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain) can ever fall into the main and avowed Channell of Eccleſiaſtical tradition; Indeed it is likely that <hi>Cerinthus</hi> the Heretick to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie his new device in that particular, fathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it on Saint <hi>John</hi> as whiſpered to him by Chriſt in confidence; and from him <hi>Papias</hi> that was an eaſie and ſimple man, taking it, paſſed by his name, and vouched only the Apoſtles, which ſome believed as a private truth, and others denied, as is apparent.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>December 26, 1638.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and faithfull Servant <hi>K. D.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:169831:14"/>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Nobleſt Couſin, and beſt friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Beg your pardon, for making you ſo ſlow a return of my humble thanks for your excellent Letter of the 26 of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember;</hi> and I ſhould have needed your pardon much more, if your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in it had been leſſer. The exceſſe of them in ſuch variety of obligations, juſtifies me in the leaſure I take to taſte and enjoy each endearing circumſtance apart; weighing and comparing with one another the ſeverall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights I ow you, whilſt every where I finde my ſelf either courted by him I love moſt, or applauded by him I emulate moſt, or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the perſon whoſe abilities I admire moſt; and all this by you dear Couſin, the prime object of my nobleſt affections. My heart is ſo much affected with theſe favours, that were this Letter (or rather Volumne, whoſe bulk may well affright you with the trouble it threatens) filled with nothing but acknowledgments, it would fall as ſhort of ſatisfaction to my ſelf in the thankfull part, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I fear it will of giving it you in the reſt that it treats of. But as in the firſt it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for me to utter the hundredth part of my thoughts, ſo in the other could I expreſs all and more then ever I can think of, I ſhould yet deſpair of efficacy to convince you by any
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169831:15"/>thing that can flow from a Pen animated with ſuch dull reflections as mine, which here notwithſtanding I venture to ſet down chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in obedience to your commands in the cloſe of your Letter, and partly through fear that I might elſe in ſome kinde incurr the tax, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Hypocriſy if I ſhould by ſilence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs an aſſent in matters of Religion where I am not convinced, or of perverſneſs, ſhould I d ſſent without ſhewing cauſe for it; which I ſhall here endeavour to manifeſt, but ſtill with this proteſtation, that could I admit of ſuch a doctrin, that in the affaire of our faith I ought to be ſwayed by any humane authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, either of one or many, I ſhould at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant publiſh a valediction to my opinions, what great wits ſoever may ſuſtain them, as willingly as I do here grant you the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence above the higheſt that I have known.</p>
               <p>And here in the firſt place I do moſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſh I could concurr with you in all the reſt, as I do in the Introduction of your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe, that ſo I might be united to you in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, as I am moſt intirely in affection. I joyne with you in full admiration of the Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Learning, and Integrity of thoſe reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers of the Church, whoſe Lives, whoſe Zeales, whoſe Deaths abundantly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited that title with everlaſting celebrations of their memories; theit veracity I attribute
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169831:15"/>infinitely unto, from a due conſideration of all thoſe happy circumſtances wherewith your eloquence authorizes it. You cannot aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate their impieties enough, who would of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to exclude ſuch ſages from being witneſſes in the moſt important matters of Religion: If any former ſlip of my pen can be but wreſted to ſuch an injuſtice, let me purge my ſelf by a ſolemn Recantation. But I hope my words imported not any ſuch ſenſe, I am ſure my ſenſe intended not any ſuch words; thoſe of my Letter were as I remember, that I could not admit them for witneſſes Authentick e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, whereon to paſs a Verdict in many caſes of Religion: Wherein by two reſtricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I am ſafely protected from any juſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of ſo unjuſt a negative, ſince the one by the very exception of many caſes, attributes to their teſtimony a validity in many, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther allows it an inducing power in the very denying it a convincing one, and tends no way to an excluſion, but only to a qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their evidence. Many indeed are the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes wherein I hold their Teſtimonials moſt ſacred and unqueſtionable; ſuch are the grand Fundamentals of Chriſtianity, the doctrine of believing in one God, of the incarnation, the Paſſion, the Reſurrection, and ſome other the conſtitutive Articles of Chriſtian Faith. Theſe (to uſe your own terms) were mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169831:16"/>indeed that concern'd their Art and Trade, matters indeed whereon their own and their poſterities Salvation undoubtedly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended, matters indeed that challenged their whole care and attention, both to receive them rightly, and transferr them faithfully. In theſe, when they tell us (as they often do plainly and unanimouſly) what they were taught, and what they found believed gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally through the whole Church: Let their affirmation be as definitive as <hi>Pythagoras</hi>'s to his Diſciples, in theſe it is too mild a word to ſay, have they not reaſon to take it unkindly to be rejected? Be it ſacrilege but to queſtion their veracity; but on the other ſide many ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes too there are wherein I can in no wiſe venter to give ſentence upon their evidence; Such are moſt, if not all the now controverted poynts, between the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church and ours, and as in my former Letter, levelling at theſe, I could not admit the Fathers for witneſſes authentical enough, whereon to paſs a Verdict in many caſes of Religion; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I muſt again profeſs in this, that I am as farr as ever from allowing them in theſe ſuch a determining or convincing Authority; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of ſuch an over ruling teſtimony, though they bear the name of witneſſes, are judges in effect, and they do give the Law, though another pronounce it. Now to be Judges,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169831:16"/>I could cite you many paſſages wherein they themſelves do utterly renounce the pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and you ſay your ſelf, that their mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty will not let them be troubled when they are recuſed for ſuch. Neither will I wrong that vertue of theirs ſo much, as to embrace their teſtimonies with any cloſer adherence then it ſelf deſires. For be they what they will in point of interpreting to us the Doctrins of Church and Scripture, I am ſure they are the beſt declarers and limiters of their own, both for their proper ſenſe, and the degrees of our receiving them. Now that I have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained the ſenſe of my former Letter, let me tell you the deſigne both of that and this; It was to expreſs unto you in the generall (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly avoiding particular queſtions) how little certainty or ſatisfaction, I think, can be found on either ſide, that ſhall rely on the Fathers teſtimonies for a clear determination of our differences. I confeſs I lancht into the Ocean of them with eager hopes of ſuch a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, and from them at length can draw juſt as certain concluſions as Sea-men of the Soyle and dimenſions of old <hi>Braſill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reaſons prevalent with me of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty, or rather in my conceipt impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of drawing out of the Fathers any ſuch proofs either way in our controverſies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an inquiring and judicious perſon ſhould be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169831:17"/>obliged to relie and acquieſce, are ſo amply and ſo learnedly ſet down by Mr. <hi>Dailby</hi> in <hi>Emploides peres,</hi> that I think little of mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial or weighty can be ſaid on this Subject, that his rare and pierceing obſervation hath not anticipated: But becauſe you will expect from me ſomewhat more then a bare reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, take in ſhort the chief inducements I will ſet down as briefly and perſpicuouſly as I can; not to inſiſt upon the more frequent ones, namely, the few writings extant of the Primitive Doctors of the firſt, ſecond, and third ages after Chriſt; The many ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, children that bear the name of Fathers, they do not ſo much as <hi>Ore</hi> refer; the alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, raſures, and inſertions which through ignorance, fraud, or maliciouſneſs, have defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, maimed, and corrupted even thoſe few monuments that remain of venerable antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; I ſay, (not to dwell upon theſe, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that in your fair and noble way of ratioci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, you will not draw arguments from any, but ſuch as are on both ſides received for intire and ligitimate pieces, differences being rightly reconcileable only by ſuch mediums as both parties conſent in) thoſe which ſeem of greateſt force with me to invalidate their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in our queſtions, are theſe Four.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Their contradictions to one another.</p>
               <p>Secondly, their variance from themſelves.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:169831:17"/>
               <p>Thirdly, their repugnances both to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, and laſtly, Their want of ability in many points of our controverſies; in moſt, of will to decide them.</p>
               <p>Their thwartings of one another both in their writings, and votes in Councels, will eaſily appear to any man that ſhall but with indifferent obſervation ſurvey their works; and this in matters of government, of practiſe, and of belief, which are the three particulars, wherein you adviſe me out of the Fathers to judge the conformity of your Church, or ours to antiquity.</p>
               <p>For their Claſhings in point of government, to name the ſuperiority of the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> will be enough to call to your memory the Epiſtles of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 53. <hi>ad Anatol.</hi> 54. <hi>ad Martian.</hi> 55. <hi>ad Pul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>her.</hi> 59. <hi>ad Martian.</hi> 61. <hi>ad Juvenal.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Leo</hi> contrary to the 28. Canon of the Fathers of the Councel of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> who had elevated that of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to an equal height with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And likewiſe thoſe Epiſtles of <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, 32. <hi>ad Maurit.</hi> 34. <hi>Conſtant. L.</hi> 4. wherein he enveighs in ſharpe terms againſt whoſoever ſhould take upon him the title of Univerſal Biſhop; hardly reconcilable with thoſe paſſages of the Fathers that the Roman Doctors cite for the Popes ſupremacy, and leaſt of all with the practice of <hi>Boniface</hi> the 3d,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169831:18"/>that ſoon after aſſumed the Appellation.</p>
               <p>To name the queſtion of Appeals to <hi>Rome</hi> will ſuffice to draw an acknowledgment from you, of the great conteſtations between the Affrican Biſhops and the Roman, condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that point; which was likewiſe oppoſitely decreed by the Synods of <hi>Sardis</hi> and <hi>Calce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. Concil. Sard. Can.</hi> 3. 2 <hi>Concil. Calced. Can.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>To name the election of Biſhops, will be ſufficient to recal to your thoughts the direct oppoſition in that point of the Fathers, of the eighth General Councel, in their two and twentieth Canon, againſt what
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 68. <hi>p.</hi> 166</note> 
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> taught at large to be Apoſtolick tradition; to wit, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould have their votes alſo in the choice of Biſhops.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, not to dwell too long upon the leaſt material point, you will eaſily be put in minde, how that which is delivered by many, and particularly by <hi>Epiphanius, p.</hi> 908. againſt <hi>Arrius</hi> for a received ſenſe of the Church, touching the preeminence of a Biſhop above a Presbyter, is flatly impugned by S. <hi>Jerom. Ep. ad Occan.</hi> 83. <hi>p.</hi> 614. and others.</p>
               <p>Their claſhings about matters of practice are altogether as obvious.</p>
               <p>Call but to minde <hi>Victors</hi> heats againſt the Biſhops of <hi>Aſia,</hi> touching the obſervance
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169831:18"/>of Eaſter day. <hi>Tatianus</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents concerning marriage, againſt the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſo many Fathers as would be endleſs to name: But becauſe the firſt was declared an Heretick for holding all marriage pollution, &amp; the laſt for eſteeming the ſecond unlawful; I beſeech you turn over S. <hi>Jerom's</hi> Epiſtles to <hi>Furia,</hi> to <hi>Agerachia,</hi> and weigh ſome paſſages in his firſt book againſt <hi>Jovinian;</hi> And then tell me not how far he is from making Marriage a Sacrament of the Church; but how far his words are from importing the others Hereſy.</p>
               <p>Caſt but your Eie upon that paſſage of <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen Cont. Celſ. l.</hi> 5. to <hi>p.</hi> 479. Where ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Angels, he ſaith, that in conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their divine nature, they are ſometimes in the Scriptures called gods, but not ſo as that we ſhould be commanded to adore them, or worſhip them with divine honors, although they be the conveyers of Gods gifts unto us: for al deſires, al prayers, al deprecations, al thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings, are to be ſent up to God the Lord of all things, by the high Prieſt who is above all Angels, who is the living word and God. Be pleaſed likewiſe to conſider the 394. <hi>pag.</hi> of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his firſt Oration againſt the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> where he teaches that God onely is to be worſhipped, &amp;c. And inform me how I ſhall comprimiſe the matter betwixt them and thoſe paſſages of other Fathers alledged
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169831:19"/>by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> for the worſhip and invocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints. <hi>L. de Beatitudine ſanctorum. c.</hi> 13. Where thoſe which he cites out of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> are not like the reſt ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, but they may ſtand in ſome oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition with the two above mentioned.</p>
               <p>Let me but remember you of the opinion that Hereticks ought to be baptized, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted by <hi>Optatus,</hi> by <hi>Auſtine,</hi> and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally by all that impugne the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> which was notwithſtanding moſt peremtorily main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by <hi>Tertullian, Cyprian, Ep. ad Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peium &amp; Firmilian,</hi> ſo far as that <hi>Cyprian</hi> for this cauſe brake into moſt notorious heats againſt <hi>Stephanus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> (both <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanus</hi> and <hi>Cyprian,</hi> urging tradition for contrary Doctrines) and <hi>Firmilian</hi> againſt all the Roman Church in general, ſaying, in an Epiſtle of his, which is the ſeventy fifth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s works; that <hi>Rome</hi> did not in all things obſerve the tradition of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and in vain boaſted of their Authority. Accord I beſeech you that paſſage of S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> Serm. 17. <hi>de verbis Apoſt. (Injuria eſt pro Martyre orare)</hi> with the practiſe of the Church in that point, which appears to have been general, and is recorded in divers of the Fathers; as <hi>Clemens, Cyprian, Auſtin</hi> 17. <hi>Serm. de verbo Apoſt.</hi> and particularly by <hi>Epiphani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> againſt <hi>Aerius, p.</hi> 911. Laſtly, in point of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169831:19"/>confeſſion &amp; penitence be pleaſed to confront thoſe paſſages of <hi>Chryſoſtome: Homil. de poenit. &amp; confeſ.</hi> It is not neceſſary (ſaith he) that thou ſhouldeſt confeſs in the preſence of witneſſes, let the inquiry of thy offences be made in thy thought, let this Judgment be without a witneſs, let God only ſee thee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing. And again, in <hi>Epiſt. ad Heb. c.</hi> 12. <hi>Hom.</hi> 31. I do not ſay to thee bring thy ſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Stage, nor accuſe thy ſelf unto others; and likewiſe that of St. <hi>Auguſtine, Confeſ. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. What have I to doe with men, that they ſhould hear my Confeſſions, as though they could heal my diſeaſes? Be pleaſed. I ſay to confront theſe with ſome paſſages of other Fathers cited by <hi>Arcudius</hi> upon that ſubject; and likewiſe by <hi>Bellarmine, l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>de Poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiâ.</hi> and confeſs the Fathers in matter of practiſe, as well as of government, irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable.</p>
               <p>Their contradictions in matters of Belief, are infinite; I ſhall only ſumme up ſuch as I eſteem moſt important, either in the points them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves which they concern, or in relation to our controverſies in the Doctrine of the Trinity: That of <hi>Juſtine Martyr, p.</hi> 357. againſt <hi>Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon,</hi> which cannot be ſolved from making a diſtinction of nature betwixt the Father and the Son: That of <hi>Tertullian, adverſ. Prax. c.</hi> 9.10. <hi>Pater tota ſubſtantia eſt, Filius vero
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169831:20"/>derivatio totius et portio;</hi> and many other paſſages in the ſame book: That of <hi>Origen tract. in Joan. tom.</hi> 3. where he implyes little leſs, as <hi>Genebrard</hi> obſerves, then that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is as much above the Son and the Holy Ghoſt, as they above the Creatures. That of <hi>Theodoret, part</hi> 3. <hi>concil. Epheſ. p.</hi> 496. where refuting <hi>Cyrils</hi> ninth <hi>Anathema,</hi> he ſaith, that in it <hi>Cyril</hi> doth anathematiſe all the Apoſtles, and the Arch-Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> himſelf, whilſt impiouſly and blaſphemouſly, (they are his words) he curſeth ſuch as do not beleeve the Holy Ghoſt to proceed from the Son: I can eaſilyer accord theſe Doctors which <hi>Arrius,</hi> then with <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> or the three hundred and eighteenth Fathers of the firſt <hi>Nicene</hi> Councel: Of the ſtate of the Soul after death, in point of reward and puniſhment; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe concerning Chriſt's deſcent into Hell. I could here cite you multitudes of oppoſitions; but I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak of theſe in another place.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, touching the Euchariſt, in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the moſt important Article of any we dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in, let me marſhall up the Fathers oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſomewhat more at large; That of <hi>Juſtin in Apol.</hi> 2. The ſanctified food (ſaith he) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with our fleſh and blood by converſion, are nouriſhed, we are taught to be the fleſh and blood of Jeſus incarnate, being made ſuch by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169831:20"/>the word of prayer, after the ſame manner as Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour by the Word of God took on him fleſh and blood for our ſalvation. How will it ſuit with the latter part of the fortieth <hi>Chap.</hi> of <hi>Tertull lib.</hi> 4. againſt <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,</hi> where his whole Argument runs upon this, That in the Euchariſt, the Bread and Wine are the figure and repreſentation of Chriſts body, (for it would have been a very extravagant argument to one that denied, as <hi>Marcion</hi> did, Chriſt himſelfe to have a body of fleſh, to alledge that bread was the fleſh of his body) his words are, Having profeſt (ſaith he ſpeaking of our Saviour) a deſire to eat the Paſſover, he took bread, and having diſtributed it to his Diſciples, he made it his body, ſaying, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> that is, the Figure of my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; of which it could not have been the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, if he had not in truth a body. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, with that other paſſage of the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, <hi>lib. de anima, chap.</hi> 14. The taſte of the Wine which he conſecrated for a memoriall of his blood: and alſo with that, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. againſt <hi>Marcion, cap.</hi> 14. The bread by which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents his body; I dare not tranſlate the reſt, <hi>Etiam in Sacramentis propriis egens mendici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus creatoris.</hi> Survey that paſſage of <hi>Cyril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Hieroſol. Catech. cap.</hi> 4. under the form of bread his body is given thee, and under the form of Wine his blood, And again, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169831:21"/>and holding this for a certainty, that the bread which we ſee is not bread, though our taſte find it to be ſo: So how this will ſound with that place of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> upon the 98. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> where he bringeth in our Saviour ſpeaking of this matter after this manner: You ſhall not eat of this body which you ſee, nor drink that blood which they ſhall ſhed which will crucifie me, I have commended a certain Sacrament unto you, that being ſpiritually un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood will quicken you.</p>
               <p>Next, conſider thoſe paſſages of <hi>Gregory Niſſene</hi> quoted by <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> we beleeve (ſaith he) the bread rightly ſanctified by the word of God, to be changed into the body of God the word. And again a little after, This doth the vertue of the benediction effect, changing the nature of what we ſee (bread and wine) into the body of the Lord: To which I op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that of <hi>Theodoret Dialog</hi> 2. The myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Symboles are not removed from their own nature after ſanctification, but remain in their former ſubſtance, form and figure; And <hi>Dialog</hi> 1. Our Lord, ſaith he, in delivering thoſe myſteries, called the bread, body; and the mixture in the Cup, blood; And ſoon after ſaith he, our Saviour inverted the names, giving to his body the name of Symbole, and to the Symbole the name of his body; ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving named himſelf Vine, he called the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169831:21"/>Blood. Next let us confront that of <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome Hom. de Encoeniis;</hi> Is it bread that you ſee? is it wine? do they go into the privie like other meats? away with ſuch a thought, for as wax being put into the fire, unites it ſelf ſo in ſubſtance to it, that nothing thereof re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains; ſo imagin here that the myſteries are ſwallowed up in the ſubſtance of the body: Therefore when you approach thereunto, think not that you receive the divine body as from man, but fire from the pincers of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphime which <hi>Eſau</hi> ſaw; ſo think that you partake of the divine body, as if you joyned your lips to his pure and ſpotleſſe ſide.</p>
               <p>Confront this with that of <hi>Origen</hi> in <hi>Caep.</hi> 15. <hi>Matth.</hi> As nothing (ſayes he) is impure in it ſelfe, but is made ſo to the polluted and incredulous, by his own uncleanneſſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe; ſo, neither doth that which is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Word of God and Prayer, in its owne nature ſanctifie him that uſeth it. And for as much as belongs to that eating, we are neither defrauded of any good by the not eating, nor enricht with any good by the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſanctified bread, which for as much as it hath of materials, goes into the belly, &amp; the privy, but becomes uſefull and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall according to the proportion of faith, making the ſoule perſpicatious and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate of what is profitable.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:169831:22"/>
               <p>Laſtly to conclude this point, let me ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, <hi>Macarius Homil.</hi> 17. and <hi>Theophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact,</hi> more remote from one another in this article of faith, then in the times wherein they lived: <hi>Macarius</hi> telling us that we offer bread and wine the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of his fleſh and blood, and they which are partakers of the viſible bread, do eat the fleſh of the Lord ſpiritually. And <hi>Theophylact</hi> teaching the directly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doctrin upon the 6. of Saint <hi>John:</hi> Note here (ſaies he) that the bread which we eat in the myſteries, is not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Lords fleſh, but the very fleſh of the Lord; and let no body be troubled, that the bread ſhould be believed fleſh, ſince the bread which he did eate when he walked here, was altered into his body, and made the ſame with his holy fleſh; ſo would the wafer be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his fleſh, if Chriſt as man did eat it, will the veryeſt Sacramentary ſay.</p>
               <p>I have inſiſted the longer upon this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, as conceiving it the higheſt point of all our controverſies, and wherein the Fathers ſhould have moſt obliged us, had they left to poſteritie a right and unanimous intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, of that great myſterie of the Euchariſt: But the certaineſt concluſion I can draw from them in this and the reſt, is of the uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of concluding any thing in our differences, from thoſe that differ ſo much amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169831:22"/>
                  <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in <hi>Orat. cohort. ad Gent.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. He ſhould have my vote for a rare Muſitian that could contrive thoſe their diſcords into a Harmony, fit to be the meaſure either of our practiſe or belief.</p>
               <p>My next Reaſon is, the Fathers variance from themſelves, a quality of much more preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to them then the other: for upon contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of teſtimonies, how point-blank ſoever a Judg may fall to examine the fame and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted integrity of the witneſſes, in which if he find a difference, he will not ſtick many times to pronounce a ſentence according to the intire credit of the men; but who will ever give judgement upon ones evidence who in the ſame buſineſſe is found in contrary tales? And here I could run over moſt of the materialeſt points wherein I made my former inſtances, and produce almoſt out of every Father <hi>pro &amp; con</hi> examples, not onely of variance, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of as eminent contradiction as that of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> concerning Purgatory, in <hi>Serm.</hi> 232. <hi>de Tempore,</hi> where he flatly denies that there is any third place beſides Heaven and Hell, calling them deceivers that teach it. And likewiſe in his 21. Book <hi>de Civitate Dei,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169831:23"/>cap.</hi> 16. where he abſolutely rejects the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of any Purgatory flames before the day of Judgement, to another paſſage in <hi>Cap.</hi> 24. of <hi>Lib.</hi> 21. <hi>de Civitate Dei,</hi> where he ſeemes poſitively to affirm i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> himſelfe: but I forbear, in regard it would be tedious, and likewiſe for that I am unwilling to preſſe a point of dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation from thoſe holy Fathers (whom I reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence) further then I needs muſt, it being ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for what I intend to inferre, that they appeare oftentimes to vary from their owne poſitions in divers Articles that we diſpute of, and others fully as important; in which I may be well excuſed from the trouble to us both of alledging examples, ſince <hi>Genebrard</hi> and <hi>Pamelius</hi> thought it their beſt courſe to purge, the one <hi>(Origen)</hi> the other <hi>(Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an)</hi> from groſſe and impious errour in many places, by ſhewing how they teach the cleane contrary in others, though by the way I muſt needs ſay, that <hi>Pamelius</hi> his manner appeares to be very extravagant; for as to ſome poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous doctrines of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> a <hi>Montaniſt,</hi> he rightly applies a cure from ſome other paſſage of <hi>Tertullian</hi> a Catholick; ſo at other times, to what hee thought venemous in <hi>Tertullian</hi> a Catholick; he prepoſterouſly preſcribes an Antitidote out of <hi>Tertullian</hi> an Heretick, as you may ſee in the eighth of his <hi>Paradoxes,</hi> where he confutes an errour in his <hi>Apologe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique,</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:169831:23"/>and <hi>de Teſtimonio Animae,</hi> Bookes which that Father wrote being a Catholicke, with a paſſage of his Book <hi>de Anima,</hi> compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed when he was turned <hi>Cataphrygian;</hi> and yet who ſo forward as <hi>Pamelius,</hi> when any paſſage in ſuch bookes makes for us to cry, out away with it, 'twas a ſaying of <hi>Tertullian</hi> a Montaniſt: I may well help my cauſe the beſt I can, by this unſetledneſſe of the Fathers, ſince the nobleſt pillar of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, Cardinall <hi>Peron,</hi> ſo often wreſts their variance from themſelves ſo much to the advantage of his. See how in his reply to King <hi>James,</hi> p. 374. he makes bold with <hi>Gregory the Great,</hi> with <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> with <hi>Jerome</hi> touching the <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabees</hi> reception into the Canon; wherein I doe not think him more in the wrong in the particular, then I believe him right in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, (to wit) that the Fathers did often vary their opinions, according to their ſeverall greenneſs or maturity of ſtudies, from whence <hi>Vincentius Lyrenenſis</hi> his directions will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, <hi>cont. haereſ. c.</hi> 39. That the Fathers depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions are onely to be taken who living in the Catholick Faith and Communion holily and wiſely, did conſtantly teach and perſiſt even untill their death in Chriſt, and further ſuch only as did receive, preſerve, and deliver their doctrines all or the greateſt part, manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in one and the ſame ſenſe; wherein
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169831:24"/>what uſe ſoever ſome Papiſts make of that paſſage, I profeſſe I thinke we are ſomewhat leſſe beholding to him for the certainty of a rule and evidence to guide our faith by, then to <hi>Archimedes</hi> for his Engine to remove the World: For the Mathematitian diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abuſes us, and declares that there is not a ſolid place to be found wheron to fix his inſtrument, but th'other leaves us to that vain ſearch of an impoſſibility; for truly as the caſe ſtands, I cannot think it leſs then an impoſſibility to know (with any competent aſſurance) what (in all or almoſt any of our debated queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) the Fathers hold with all thoſe ſolid circumſtances whereon <hi>Vincentius</hi> his rule is grounded, of holineſs, wiſdom, catholickneſs, immutability of the teachers, and perpetual identitie of the doctrins ſenſe, if with years they all improved, I might be comforted a little by relying on their laſt dictamens; but as I find a S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> that with age retracted his errors, ſo on the other ſide I meet with a <hi>Tertullian</hi> that going forward in years and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, went leſs in his judgement; how happie ſhould we both be in one, that could aſſure us in the Legion of Fathers, when was the verticle point of each their eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, whether at their ſummer or winter ſolſtice; if I give you the notes of it, and tell you then only you have it certain, when they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169831:24"/>are in a perfect and palpable conjunction with Scripture, you will think it but an imperfect indication; if you ſay that then they were ariv'd to the high point of their perfection, when they were once exactly inſtructed in the full ſence of the Church, I muſt not admit of that marke whilſt you are proving the Churches receptions by theirs; and therefore if you pleaſe, let us both agree, that for either of us there is no reſolving evidence to be taken from the Fathers, that are ſo irreſolute themſelves; when you meet with a paſſage in any of them that ſtands not with your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, conceive their judgement not ripe, or rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, when they writ it, or that their recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are loſt, the ſame liberty ſhall I take in mine; for truly had Saint <hi>Auſtins</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable monument of humble ingenuity (as well as high erudition) his Retractations pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed as <hi>Origens,</hi> which as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith, he had made in an Epiſtle to <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 65. <hi>ad Pamach, et Occan.</hi>
                  </note> did before him, Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> might perhaps have had a place in ſome others Catalogue of heretiques, as well as Saint <hi>Origen</hi> in his; And truly who can ſecure us that the like miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hap hath not befallen others of the Fathers, now taxable with erronious doctrins, by the loſs perhaps of ſome after-ſurvey of their own works?</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:169831:25"/>
               <p>My Third conſideration is of the Fathers variouſneſs and repugnancies to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, practiſe, and belief, of both the Romiſh Church and ours: In which I have prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the need of examples by many of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, both of my former Letter and this, as that of the equalitie of Biſhops &amp; Presbyters, that of rebaptizing, that of Angels, that of the Millenaries, &amp;c. to which I will lonly adde, that which ſo many, and moſt particularly S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> delivers of the neceſſity of childrens partak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Euchariſt, and his rigor againſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants unbaptized; ſome of which I take to be beames, all more then motes, fit to be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of their eyes, before we can with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon reſigne up our own ſences to their gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and manuduction.</p>
               <p>My Fourth concluding reaſon, is, the want of ability in many of the Fathers, in moſt of will to determine the points of controverſie, and this I hope I may ſafely affirm without wrong, either to their abilities or good wills. A general and potential ability to reſolve dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties every ſtrong reaſon includes, if in the particulars wherein it ſhould be brought forth unto act, there concur (upon propoſal) meanes of informing ones ſelf, and a will to uſe it: Such an ability thoſe learned Fathers (rich in all the choyce endowments of ſoule) had in moſt ſingular eminence, and as it were
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169831:25"/>madneſs to rob them of thoſe, ſo I think it is neither Logicall, nor prudential, becauſe they were knowing in the general, to attribute to them an actual ability to diſcern ſuch particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar queſtions, wherein it is ſo farr from appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that they had the means of informing themſelves, or the will to uſe them, that I ſee no ſignes that in their ages they were ever in propoſal; ſuch and ſo farr from agitation or controverſie (the parents that give life and act to particular abilities) were, as I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, in the primitive times the doctrins of infallibility annexed to a Church of any one denomination, of adoring the Euchariſt for God, of Purgatory with its complements, of Indulgences, and many other choice points of our controverſies; All which I profeſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to me as unthought of for the firſt 500. years after Chriſt, as the <hi>Antipodes,</hi> or the <hi>Antartique</hi> pole to <hi>Lactantius,</hi> or <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> that tooke the heavens to be to the earth but as the flat cover of a box; In theſe I take it to be of no more derogation from them to deny their deciding abilities, then to ſay that they were not able to leave to poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, an exact Mapp of <hi>America,</hi> which was not diſcovered in ſo many hundred years, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: ſo far is it from an injurious detraction, that to imagin them ſtudious, definitive, or active in queſtions hardly ever moved, that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169831:26"/>had neither profeſt maintainers or impugners, were to imagine them idle, and Ayre-beaters, No marvail that to decide ſuch, they ſhould want wills, having neither means nor occaſion to actuate their abilities, or that they ſhould want abilities, having no provocations that might ſtimulate their wills. Thoſe primitive Champions of the Goſpel, the Fathers of the firſt 400. years, who in this buſineſs are moſt to be conſulted with, had their time, their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, their pens ſo inceſſantly exerciſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the common enemie of Chriſt, the Jews and Gentiles, or elſe againſt thoſe heynous he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques, that pretended the name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, but tended to the utter ſubverſion of it, as the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> the <hi>Samoſaterians Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiques,</hi> the <hi>Marcioniſts,</hi> and divers other blaſphemous or <hi>Chimerical</hi> innovators, that they had little leaſure to raiſe to themſelves imaginarie enemies to combate with in ſuch ſlight and trivial points as theſe we diſpute of; or if perchance any ſuch were preſented, little care to ſubdue them. But that I may not be thought to frame a diſcourſe upon two falſe ſuppoſitions: The one that our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted points are of articles of Religion, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle material; the other, that in the primitive times there were few of them in agitation, or neglected, if they were, let me tell you what induceth me to think ſo.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:169831:26"/>
               <p>For the firſt, that they were in themſelves little material, or at leaſt thought ſo by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (which is all one for our purpoſe) though now I confeſs grown highly important by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing injoyned many of them under the paine of <hi>Anathema</hi>'s, to be believed as eſſential to ſalvation) I collect out of a ſurvey of all thoſe Antient, yea and more modern rolls (where it is likely all neceſſary points of faith or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice would be recorded) where finding no newes at all of them, I think I may ſafely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them but ſlight in compariſon of what I finde there regiſtred.</p>
               <p>The firſt and prime inducement to me is, that I meet with them no where in Scripture; but this is none to you who do not allow that to be the perfect reconditory of all neceſſary Doctrines The next is, that in the Fathers ſeveral Catalogues of Hereticks, as that of <hi>Philaſtrius, Epiphanius,</hi> and S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> I finde none branded with Hereſie, for not holding thoſe Articles impoſed on mens beliefs by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and rejected by ours, whoſe note it is not likely ſuch would have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped, as had impugned any doctrines believed by them neceſſary to ſavlation: But to this perhaps you will ſay, that the denomination of Heretick was not incurred by the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that men held, but by their obſtinate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in ſuch after the Churches manifeſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169831:27"/>them, and that upon this reaſon divers who beleeved not all things neceſſary, might well miſs a place in their denumeration of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks; wherefore ſetting theſe two aſide, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe though of much force with me, yet likely to be invalide with you, I onely preſs upon your conſideration my laſt, and I think, undeniable reaſon, taken from the non-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of ſuch articles in thoſe ſeveral pieces; wherein the Fathers of ſet purpoſe and deſigne profeſſedly do ſet down all the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential doctrines of Chriſtianity agreed upon throughout the Church univerſal: Such were their Symboles, ſuch <hi>Irenaeus</hi> his unity of Faith, in <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. ſuch <hi>Origens</hi> intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to his book <hi>de principiis,</hi> ſuch <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullians</hi> rule of Faith in his preſcription a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Hereticks, ſuch <hi>Epiphanius</hi> his conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his work, which he calls the ſettlement of truth &amp; aſſurance of immortality; ſuch like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe (to fit you with ſome of all ages) was that work of <hi>Gennadius</hi> (written within theſe two hundred years) <hi>De rectâ Chriſtianorum Fide:</hi> I will not ſay in ſome of which, but in all which together, there is not one Article of Faith received by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and rejected by us, ſo much as mentioned, ſave only in <hi>Epiphanius</hi> of Chriſts diſcent into Hel; a Point variouſly and uncertainly underſtood among the Fathers; as ſhall in another place be demonſtrated.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:169831:27"/>
               <p>Now for farther proof of the little agitation or great neglect of our controverted points in the Primitive times (although it will follow of conſequence to what hath been allready al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged) yet I beſeech you let me appeal to your own obſervation: Do you know of any of the Fathers for the firſt four hundred years that hath purpoſely and of deſigne compoſed the leaſt Treatiſe of any one of our queſtions? or in ſome other tract handled them ſo much as in a formal digeſtion? Inform me I beſeech you; for I profeſs all the works that ever I have met with of them, appear to have been wholy directed either to deride the Pagans, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute Philoſophers, to convince the Jewes, to confound prodigious Hereſies, or deliver pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of good life, or elſe to expound ſome paſſages of Scripture moſt uſeful to the ſame ends: Theſe appear to me to have been the ſole objects both of their wills and abilities to combate: And ſhall we venture to give ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in our intricate diſputes upon words or paſſages, that by the by may ſeem to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern them, either caſually let fall, or directed to other purpoſes, in moſt of which in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience we finde our own opinions as rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as <hi>Whittington</hi> his turn Lord Major of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> in the ring of bells, or ſome melancholy Lover his Miſtriſſes picture in the graine of Wainſcote, and their intentions as rightly as
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169831:28"/>
                  <hi>Eudocia, Homers,</hi> and another <hi>Virgils,</hi> when they made him Evangelize; ſo little do I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard what they ſay in this our caſe; but to their ſilence I attribute much, and think it ſtrongly expreſſive, but nothing to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of thoſe that impoſe for neceſſary Articles of Faith, Doctrines that thoſe renowned O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of the Church, either never heard of, or thought not worth their mentioning.</p>
               <p>Thus noble Couſin, I have laid before you the principal reaſons that led me to deny the Fathers Teſtimonies to have ſuch a validity whereon we may juſtly paſs a verdict in our queſtions of Religion; which I beſeech you, not to take as meant in a way of further dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation from them then in thoſe very particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; for there is no man living that in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral payes them more reverence then my ſelf in the higheſt admiration of their erudition and piety. And therefore where I have mark'd out their heates againſt one another, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions; let them be underſtood to have ſprung from holy fervor and zeal in whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they were for the time perſwaded was good and true: when I note their variance from themſelves, let it recommend their inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity that would ſo clearly avow their own fallibility: when I tax them for diſſenting from us all in this age, (although S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> when the Donatiſts preſs him with antiquity,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169831:28"/>ſticks not to ſay that the younger Doctors are ſharper ſighted) yet let not my words be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven farther then this modeſt (ſince you ſo call it) flattery to our ſelves, not of ſeeing clearer or ſharper then they, but onely (by their helps) further, as dwarfs upon Gyants ſhoulders: And laſtly, when I deny them the ability to determine our points of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies let it be of no more derogation from their learning and judgement, then it were of leſſening to an Ambaſſador, or of flattery to his followers, to ſay, that at a publike audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſome of them could give a good account of the things in the lower end of the room, when he himſelf could ſay little or nothing of them, having onely paſt them by, with his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions intirely fixt upon the higher and more noble objects.</p>
               <p>Theſe were the Conſiderations that poſſeſt me when I wrote my former Letter; although I had then the leiſure but to point at a few of them, (and ſince I cannot ſpeak to you but with truth and freedom) I muſt here profeſs they remain in full force with me ſtill, your Letter having given me great contentment, but little ſatisfaction; for I can by no means yeeld, that there is any Aſſurance, much leſs infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility in the Rule which you at the firſt preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, and ſtill inſiſt on, of judging our Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies by the Fathers; namely, to uſe our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169831:29"/>of reaſon only in what they teach of themſelves, with confirmations out of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or probable Arguments; but to reſign it up in an entire and implicite Aſſent, to what they tell us they were taught, and deliver to us as delivered to them for the received ſenſe of the Church; which is to be underſtood (you ſay) not only when they uſe theſe formall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Words, That the Church hath received from the Apoſtles, and holdeth generally ſuch and ſuch a Doctrine; but at other times alſo, when they do but intimate it in their Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, (where by the way I muſt needs tell you, I ever thought intimations likelyer to beget Diſputes then to end them.) If in this poſitive Rule you reſerve a Liberty to except ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars ſo delivered, or ſome Catholick Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſo delivering them; Then without more adoe it is evident that this Way, nothing can be decided; for your Adverſaries will claim (in what thwarts them) the like liberty of excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. If you lay the Rule abſolutely generall, to wit, that what Article ſoever is delivered directly, or by imtimation from the Fathers, to have been a received Doctrine of the Church, ought to be ſwallowed for an infallible verity, it will eaſily be made appear, that this method muſt betray you, not only into ſome Proteſtant Tenents, but alſo into Beliefs on both ſides con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to be erroneous: It muſt draw you to be
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169831:29"/>a Millenary, it muſt draw you to hold a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Childrens partaking the Euchariſt; it muſt draw you to abhorr that uſe of Images as Idolatrous; and finally, it muſt force you to reject out of the Canon thoſe Books which we eſteem Apochryphall; for all theſe doe the Fathers deliver, with ſomewhat more then intimations that they were taught to them, as derived from the Apoſtles, and from generall receptions of the Catholique Church.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for the doctrine of the <hi>Millenaries,</hi> I conceive you make a right judgement of the originall thereof from <hi>Papias,</hi> whom St. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> (the beſt Critick in Eccleſiaſticall Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity) ſayes to have been the firſt Authour of it; which error it is probable the ſaid <hi>Papias</hi> ran into, either by a flattery to win upon the Jewes, or elſe, as you ſay, by the groſſe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of a Text in the twentieth of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalypſe,</hi> himſelfe being one but of a dull and eaſie ſpirit, which being taken from him by thoſe that reverenced the antiquity and piety of the man, was delivered with recommendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their ſucceſſors, and ſo took poſſeſſion of moſt of the Doctors of the following Ages. As for that of <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> I believe with <hi>Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Senenſis,</hi> that it was a diſtinct hereſie, which fed carnall men with hopes of beaſtly and ſenſuall delights: for it is not likely that a doctrine taken from ſuch an arch Heretick as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169831:30"/>
                  <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> could have found ſuch reception among the Catholick Fathers; and leaſt of all is it probable, that <hi>Cerinthus</hi> could have fathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it upon St. <hi>John,</hi> whom the Apoſtle is ſaid to have deteſted ſo much, that <hi>Iraeneus, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>adverſ. haereſ.</hi> (a chiefe Champion of the Millenaries) in that very Chapter where (as you ſay) he reckons up the ſucceſſions of Biſhops in divers Churches, relates, that when St. <hi>John</hi> was entring into a Bath where <hi>Cerinthus</hi> waſhed himſelfe, St. <hi>John</hi> no ſooner ſaw him, but he ſtept back, crying out, Let us forſake the place, leſt that enemy of truth draw down the houſe upon our heads: a fit Authour for ſo foule a Doctrine, but one very unlikely to be believed acquainted with Chriſts whiſpers to St. <hi>John.</hi> But as this enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous part which paſſes alſo with moſt under the name of <hi>Millenaries</hi> hereſie, was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally condemned: ſo the other more ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of <hi>Papias,</hi> was and is farre from being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved at this day, either by your Church or ours, much more from finding ſo firm and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire aſſent as you will be obliged to give it by your rule of ſwallowing for unqueſtionable and infallible what doctrine ſoever the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers deliver as taught unto them, and to be the generall ſenſe of the Chriſtian Church in their times: And for proofe that it was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered for ſuch by <hi>Papias</hi> (who gloried in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169831:30"/>more then in being a carefull collector of the doctrines taught by the Apoſtles <hi>viva voce</hi>) I referre you nlyto <hi>Nicephorus Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtus Hiſt. Eccleſ. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Juſtine Martyr p.</hi> 307. delivered it for ſuch a paſſage in his <hi>Dial.</hi> with <hi>Tryphon,</hi> will eaſily teſtifie, where he ſaith, that he, and all in all parts orthodox Chriſtians held it, and calls them Chriſtians onely in name, with many other circumſtances of aggravation, that denied it. It is true (as you ſay) hee confeſſes a little before, that ſome good and honeſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did not acknowledge it; but this may be an argument how careleſſe, and oftentimes repugnant to themſelves ſome of the Fathers were in their writings, or elſe how little ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous of ſetting to doubtfull doctrines that ſeale which you account ſo ſacred; but it can no way ſalve him from having taught it with thoſe circumſtances which you eſteeme the notes of infallibility. That <hi>Iraeneus</hi> took it and taught it to be of tradition from Chriſt, I think is ſo manifeſt, that it were ſuperfluous to inſiſt upon particular paſſages in that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, to omit <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and others, who clearly (me thinks) imply as much, though not in the very terms. What can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe more a doctrine rightly delivered, and generally received, then <hi>Lactantius, lib.</hi> 7. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169831:31"/>c.</hi> 26. his concluſion of his long diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon this ſubject; <hi>haec eſt doctrina ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum Prophetarum, quam Chriſtiani ſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, hoc eſt Chriſtiana ſapientia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, For the neceſſity of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens partaking of the Euchariſt, although the evident practiſe of the Church for the firſt ſix hundred years, according to all our records of antiquity, might excuſe me from proving by any particular inſtance, that ſome of the Fathers taught the neceſſity of it for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived tradition; yet take this of St. <hi>Auſtin lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de peccat. mer. &amp; remiſſ. c.</hi> 24. rightly (ſaith he) do the Punick Chriſtians call Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme by no other names but health and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; nor the Sacraments of Chriſts body by no other then life, <hi>unde niſi ex antiquâ, ut ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimo, et Apoſtolica traditione qua Eccleſiae Chriſti inſitum tenent praeter Baptiſmum et participationem Dominicae menſae, non ſolum non ad Regnum Dei ſed nec ad ſalutem et vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam aeternam poſſe quemquam hominum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venire.</hi> So direct a paſſage, that I ſee not how in this point you can avoid the neceſſity either of retracting your rule of aſſurance, or of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring an <hi>Anathema</hi> of the Councel of Trent, <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 21. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Can.</hi> 4. againſt any that ſhould hold this very opinion which you finde ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, and ſo Majeſtically ſealed by Saint <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:169831:31"/>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertul. lib. de I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dololatria, Orig. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Cont. Celſ. Arnob. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Lactan. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap. ult. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han. Ep. ad Johan. Hieroſol. inter oper. Hier. Epiſt.</hi> 60. <hi>Ambr. de ſuga. Secul. cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Auguſt. de fide cap.</hi> 7.</note> Thirdly, for the uſe of Images (a point likewiſe of my former letter) to which you ſay that the Fathers do not uſe the Authority or Tradition of the Church to beat it down, I am confident you will confeſs that affirmation a ſlip of obſervation or memory, when you ſhall but caſt your Eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe paſſages of the Fathers for brevity ſake quoted onely in the Margin; where doubtleſs in ſome at leaſt you will finde the interdiction of them ſo deeply ſtampt with your ſuppoſed great ſeal of Chriſtianity, that if you ſtick to your own rule, it will not be enough to ſpeak indifferently of the matter with the Moderator on your ſide, but you muſt be as rigid and ſevere againſt them as you can imagine any warm brother would be at <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denbourgh;</hi> for I do not think any Zealot of them all can be more invective in this point then moſt of thoſe Fathers were, many to the abhorring of the very Trade of Imagery; but becauſe you do inſiſt ſomewhat upon juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the contrary practiſe at this day in the Romiſh Church, I muſt beg leave to run over your Allegations, and to acquaint you freely how unſatisfied I am in the particulars.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place you evade the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Primitive Fathers, voucht formerly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169831:32"/>by me, namely, of <hi>Juſtine</hi> and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> by ſaying, In regard that Idolatry was then freſh in the memory and practice of the world, they might well think it dangerous to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that which the following Governours of the Church might afterwards introduce up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a good ground of raiſing devotion in the people, ſince things of that nature, you ſay, may be convenient at one time, and unfit at another.</p>
               <p>And in the next, you labour to juſtifie the uſe of Images now, by ſaying, Firſt, that as ſtrong Arguments, and as pregnant paſſages of Scripture are produced for it, as formerly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. Secondly, by alledging that theſe times are ſecure from the danger of Idolatry, And laſtly, by affirming that a great good ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in them.</p>
               <p>To your infirming of thoſe Ancient Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities in this point, it will be ſufficient to put you in minde, that divers of the more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Fathers farr enough removed from the vicinity of Paganiſm after Chriſtianity had taken poſſeſſion of the world, were as perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptory <hi>Iconoclaſts</hi> as thoſe two I pitcht upon. And for the variance of practice upon variance of times, your reaſon might hold, had they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the Religious uſe of Images onely as inconvenient, and not as in its own Nature unlawfull, but what's ſimply unlawfull at one
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169831:32"/>time, cannot be lawfull at another, without a precept from God (which you ſay) in your firſt words upon this ſubject, You did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve to have been given herein.</p>
               <p>To your firſt juſtification of this Practiſe, I muſt needs ſay, that for the ſtrong Arguments for it, to which I am yet a ſtranger, I ſhould be glad to be acquainted with them, but for the Texts of Scripture ſo pregnant as you ſpeak of, truly I ſhould be ſorry to meet with them, for although where I finde in holy Writt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing repugnances, and difficult intricacies, I am as apt as any body (having perhaps moſt reaſon for it of any) to accuſe my own ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and to preſerve all veneration to what I finde there; yet I confeſs it would trouble me much, and be of dangerous temptation, ſhould I meet with a paſſage in the ſacred volumne, as palpably direct for the uſe of Images, as I am ſure the ſecond Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is againſt it.</p>
               <p>For your Second Allegation, that theſe times are ſecure from the danger of Idolatry, ſome proofs would be neceſſary, ſince I am farr from underſtanding them to be ſo; were that ſinne committed then only when the outward or inward act of veneration ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with that belief, and reliance which belongs to the Creator is exhibited to, and terminated in the creature, I ſhould then
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169831:33"/>be of your opinion, and pronounce theſe times in little danger of Idolatry; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, my vote ſhould alſo go to acquit all ages from the Crime, as well as the preſent. For I do not think that the fowleſt Idolaters of the Heathen ever arrived to that height of ſtupidity, as to take thoſe low and materiall objects of their devotion for God Almighty: Nay, the more beſtiall their Idolatry was, as of the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> in worſhiping the vileſt creatures, the leſſe probability is there that they conceived the eſſence of the Deity to dwell under thoſe contemptible forms that they adored; as I think the Jewes little guilty of believing that the Calfe which they had made of their ear-rings, though ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly deified by their veneration, was the great God that hath wrought his wonders among them: but ſince it is as formal idolatry to frame to ones ſelfe, out of low, limited &amp; corruptible formes, reſemblances of the incomprehenſible Deity, and to impart to them any kinde of divine honour, whether you pleaſe to call them of adoration, of ſervice, or of pious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſince to worſhip the true God after an unfitting manner, involves men as well in this ſin, as the ſervice of a falſe God: ſince (I ſay) theſe practiſes as well as the other, amount to Idolatry; yea ſuch, as for my part, I believe the Jews &amp; Pagans were rarely guilty of any
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169831:33"/>greater amidſt their higheſt abominations. I muſt profeſſe I think the world at preſent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly liable to the ſin; yea, many of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Church deeply plunged therein by the eaſie abuſe, if not by the ſingle uſe of Images in their prayers: and this not onely the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler ſort, but even the learned Doctors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if one may believe them of themſelves. <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquine</hi> ſayes, <hi>Summ. part.</hi> 3. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 25. <hi>Art.</hi> 3. and hath many followers in it, That the ſame reverence is to be given to the Image of Chriſt, that is to Chriſt himſelfe; and ſeeing Chriſt is adored with the adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Latria,</hi> that his Image alſo is to be ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the adoration of <hi>Latria;</hi> ſo farre is that great Doctor and his Sectators tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whom I doe chuſe much rather to brand with the imputation of Idolatry, then many others of his own ſide, as learned, that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne his doctrine with ſacriledge; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as I conceive, no medium between thoſe two impieties, where one denies adoration of the higheſt kinde, to that unto which another payes it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, for the great good which you ſay appeares in the uſe of Images; I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it doth but appeare: it is pretended they help the memory, and excite devotion in the people. If by aids of memory, be underſtood onely in the generall, that the lively repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169831:34"/>of ſome holy Hiſtorie, is likely to call better thoughts into our mindes then a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaner; I like it well; by the ſame reaſon that the courſeſt picture of CHRIST cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, ought in a good Chriſtians Cabinet to take the wall of a <hi>Venus</hi> of <hi>Titian;</hi> the one being apt to mortifie us through the ſame ſenſe whereby the other may inflame us: but if by the help of memory any thing be meant of more particular aſſiſtance in the directing of our prayers, I think Images doe juſt as much good in that point, as the art of memory would doe to your excellent naturall one, that is, help to dizzy and diſtract it: Or if by excitement to devotion, be meant any particular ſtimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and guidance to the righteſt way of true devotion, or furniſhing us with a proper means of addreſſing it to the right and origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall object, I conceive them then ſo far from being of good uſe in this kinde, that I hold their very ſtimulations to devotion dangerous, they excite, they warm the zeale of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, 'tis true, but with thoſe ſtrange fires that cauſed ſuch combuſtions in Iſrael, whilſt ſo many (as <hi>Gul. Parienſis de Legibus cap.</hi> 23. confeſſes) not diſtinguiſhing between the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and the thing, adore the picture in ſtead of what it repreſents; wherein farre leſſe ſinful were a luke-warm piety rightly applied, then the ardenteſt devotion miſdirected, by how
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169831:34"/>much ſins of omiſſion are more pardonable then of act, and to worſhip the true God leſſe intenſly, then to ſerve a falſe one zealouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Of this danger there cannot be a better witneſſe, for all his mincing of the matter, then <hi>Gregory</hi> the great (in his Epiſtle to <hi>Cirenus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Marcelles,</hi> in which that paſſage is which you cite) who there adviſeth the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop to excuſe to his flock the breaking down of Images in the Church, by alledging that he was forc'd to that Act by the peoples abuſing that to adoration, which was erected onely for inſtruction of the ignorant and illiterate in matter of hiſtory. The Biſhop truly was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding unto him, for furniſhing him with ſuch an excuſe, which might ſerve to juſtifie all the fierceſt Iconoclaſts, ſince all the good that imagination can preſent in the uſe of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges throughout the whole Univerſe, cannot amount to recompence the miſchiefe of one poore ſoules betraying to Idolatry.</p>
               <p>For my part I doe conceive, that good uſe might be made of holy pictures, but hardly by the vulgar, which makes me wonder at that ſaying of <hi>Gregory</hi> which you glance at, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſeems to adapt them to the ignorant, ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them the books of the unlettered: For beſides the ſmall Divinity (me thinks there is ſo little Philoſophy) in the ſaying; Books tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they may be for ſuch Ignoramuſes as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169831:35"/>read and will not heare, wherein they may perhaps learn matters of fact (as ſome children that have an averſion from their bookes, are taught their letters in Dice) but are very unlikely to profit in any right devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; had he appropriated the uſe of Images ſolely to the moſt knowing and ſpeculative, it would have been more tollerable: ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps one might believe likely from materiall and ſenſible repreſentments to raiſe ſpirituall meditations ſurpaſſing ſenſe; and by the greater livelihood and glory of the object, to perfect the more, and purifie their abſtraction from all ſervile dependance on materiality; ſome ſuch extaticall Contemplator as <hi>Diony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> that beares the name of the <hi>Areopagite</hi> (a notable Diſciple I am ſure of <hi>Plato's,</hi> what ever he was of <hi>Pauls</hi>) might perchance have an Art of erecting his ſoule by Images, to ſome admirable intelligence of the true one onely to be adored. If they were hideous and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, he could inform you that the propereſt preſentation of inviſible things to ſenſe, is by the unlikelieſt repreſentations; and that in their con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emplation our ſoule is more elevated by
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dionyſ Arcop. de Caeleſt. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarch.</hi> cap. 2.</note> diſagreeing Images, then by reſembling ones. And therefore that the Celeſtiall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are expreſt unto us uſually in Scriptures by ſuch Images as are irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169831:35"/>with the Originals they ſignifie, as of Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, Lions, Bulls, &amp;c. to which I will be bold only to ſay this, that I beleeve more would have aſſented to his ſpeculatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I am ſure more would have underſtood it, had he inferred, that ſince God was pleaſed to paint out himſelf &amp; his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring ſpirits in ſuch incompatible Images, we ſhould not attempt the making ſuch repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations as we doe of thoſe incomprehenſible forms. If the Images were of ſweet proportion &amp; luſter, he would finde perchance a way in his negative Divinity, the more beauteous they were, to attribute the more to thoſe celeſtiall natures, by
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dionyſ. Arcop. de Div. nom. c.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp; de Myſt. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. c.</hi> 2.</note> removing from the ſplendidſt glories of the ſenſe, all capacity of proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with their ſpirituall perfection; ſuch uſes as theſe of Images, might perhaps be credible with the <hi>Pere Golu</hi> of a <hi>Dionyſius</hi> in his rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who could fancy to himſelfe all the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Church, and the formal and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtick diviſions of our Temples, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of that at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> before that our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion had any but private houſes, or barnes; who could perform religious viſits to the body of the virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> either foure yeares after ſhe was dead, or as many before himſelf was a Chriſtian, for elſe his Eccleſiaſticall Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and his Epiſtle to <hi>Policarp</hi> cannot ſtand with Chronology. But to conceive that the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169831:36"/>vulgar, the ignorant, ſuch whoſe ſouls are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſt (as you ſay) in the ſaeculence of matter, ſuch as <hi>Mahomet</hi> fitted his law to, the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, to whom as <hi>Avicenna</hi> ſayes in his book <hi>de Almahad</hi> their Prophet, was fain to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe a heaven proportionable to their ſoules, all of ſenſuality, ſweets to be taſted, beauties viſible, delights palpable, ſuch who to abſtract from matter, and to conceive any thing of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporeall natures, had need be raiſed by ſome rarer Art then <hi>Amphibions</hi> Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, which becauſe they partake of both Natures, of the one in their inherence, of the other in conſideration; are called by <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clus,</hi> the bridge and ladder to pure and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat abſtractions; ſuch in whom <hi>Tertullians</hi> ſaying erroneous in the generall, is verified in their particular, <hi>Anima animae ſenſus eſt.</hi> To preſcribe I ſay, that ſuch ſhould be taught, as <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith the ignorant ought to be by I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, whom to adore (he being infinite and inviſible) or how to adore (ſince that muſt be free and ſpiritually) by fixing and faſtning them upon viſible, finite, corporeall and engaging objects of the ſenſe, appeares to me as judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a courſe, as if a Pilot ſhould caſt an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor that his ſhip might ſaile the faſter. Let me period this queſtion with a much more divine, as well as more <hi>Platonicke</hi> ſentence of <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> All ſorts of Images
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169831:36"/>(ſayes he) are directly forbidden by <hi>Moſes,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Now laſtly, for concluſion of this part of my diſcourſe, to ſhew, that according to your Rule, you muſt reject out of the Canon thoſe bookes which we eſteeme <hi>Apocryphall,</hi> I need no other proofs then that of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Praef. in lib. Solo. Epiſt.</hi> 115.</note> 
                  <hi>Jerom, Judith</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Tobiae &amp; Macca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baeorum libros legit quidem Eccleſia, ſed inter Canonicas Scripturas non recipit,</hi> added unto that of <hi>Ruffinus</hi> (his great adverſary in other things) in his expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apoſtles <hi>Creed,</hi> ſo ſolemne a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and alone ſo ſufficient, as being moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently ſignalized with all your circumſtances of infallibility, that I cannot forbeare ſetting it down at large: <hi>Ideo</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quae ſunt novi &amp; veteris Teſtamenti volumina quae ſecundum majorem traditionem per ipſum Spiritum ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum inspirata creduntur, &amp; Eccleſiae Chriſti tradita, competens videtur, in hoc loco eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti numero ſicut ex patrum monumentis accepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus deſignare.</hi> And accordingly he denume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates onely thoſe bookes received by us for Canonicall, and goes on, <hi>Haec ſunt quae Patres intra Canonem concluſerunt ex quibus Fidei noſtrae aſſertiones conſtare voluerunt: ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169831:37"/>tamen eſt quod &amp; alii qui non Canonici, ſed Eccleſiaſtici a majoribus appellati ſunt:</hi> and reckons up all thoſe which we reject; and thus concludes, <hi>Haec nobis à patribus, ut dixi, tradita opportunum viſum eſt hoc in loco deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare ad inſtructionem eorum qui prima ſibi Eccleſiae ac Fidei elementa ſuſcipiunt, ut ſciant ex quibus ſibi fontibus verbi Dei haurienda ſint pocula.</hi> Should I meet with any Article of the Romiſh Church ſignalized, as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſo eminently as this of ours, with all the circumſtances, which you count the notes of infallibility; as little as I agree with you in the generall, I confeſs it would ſtagger me in the particular: and therefore I doe not ſee how you can avoid either, the retracting your rule of aſſurance, or by concurring in this point with us to incurr another heavie <hi>Anathema</hi> of the Councell of TRENT, <hi>Seſſione quarta.</hi> To theſe ſeveral inſtances I could add many more as conſiderable in other points both of Government, Practiſe, and Belief, but that ſo redious a recitation would ſeem a deſigne to weary as well as convince you: beſides that, to deſtroy the univerſality of your maxime, and to bring you to exceptions, one pregnant ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is as good as a thouſand, and that is all I need to do: For as I ſaid before, if in your poſitive rule you once take the liberty to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt particular Doctrines, or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169831:37"/>Fathers delivering them, I may then with out any further proof flatly conclude, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be this way concluded, ſince your adverſaries will likewiſe claim in whatſoever ſhall thwart them, an equal liberty of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting.</p>
               <p>Now Couſin, give me leave to examine a little neerer, the three grounds whereon you build the pretended certainty of this Method, in reſolving your differences out of the Fathers declarations; as I collect your ſenſe they are theſe. Firſt, That they were faithful Collectors of the general traditions of the Church in their times. Secondly, that they are ſincere conveyers of them to us: And Thirdly, that the traditions collected and conveyed by them are infallible. Should I grant them all to be true, it would not follow that they were ſufficient, till it did appear (which I think never will, though for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent we will ſuppoſe it) that there were gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral traditions preſerved in the Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all thoſe points which we diſpute of; but unleſs they appear to be true, I am ſure they cannot paſs for ſufficient.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That they were faithful Collectors of all the traditions of the Church; where, in faithful, I ſuppoſe, you compriſe careful &amp; able for in the other ſingle ſenſe of fidelity, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hath moſt proper relation to the following
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169831:38"/>condition of Conveyers; induſtry and ability being as fully requiſite in this the Collecting part as integrity: To this I ſay, that as in one place I have formerly profeſt how I beleeve them ſuch faithful Collectors of the Churches receptions, that is, careful and able, as well as ſincere in many things of greateſt importance; ſo in another, I think, I have ſaid enough whereby to prove it unlikely that in things of leſs moment, ſuch as our controverſies, the Primitive Fathers did applie their care and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities to ſound the bottome of them; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this way of collecting the traditions of the Church concerning them or any other. Induſtry requiring alwayes ſtimulations in the particular buſineſſes, where we are to expect it; and likewiſe ſome leaſure &amp; remiſſion from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſſing occupations. Both which the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Fathers totally wanted, by little provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in our caſes, and inceſſant allarms in more weighty ones. So that to your firſt ground, I will onely make of new this demand: Was the knowledge and Collection of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches traditions &amp; receptions eaſie and evident to all careful inveſtigators, or hard and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult? If the latter, which I beleeve, ſince ſo many circumſtances are requiſite to the exact knowledge of the Churches traditions; as firſt certain evidence, what is that Church univerſal whoſe traditions are ſo ſacred. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169831:38"/>a clear and unconfus'd delivery of the ſame unto them; &amp; laſtly, not only an exquiſite apprehenſion of the ſubſtance of all the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, but a perfect intelligence of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and neceſſities either of belief or practiſe wherein the Church did hold them: if thus hard, I ſay, and intricate, the Fathers being men, and liable (as you confeſs) to error, how can we be ſecured that they did not oftentimes mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake them, ſince it is evident that ſometimes they did? If facill and obvious which is likelyeſt you take them to be, ſince you prefer them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Scriptures, becauſe that you ſay is difficult; how comes it that they diſagree having a plain eaſie and infallible Directory, whereby to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate and conform their judgments? And truly Couſin, ſuppoſing it ſuch, I know not how to free divers of them that diſſent from one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in matters where tradition is vouched from the imputation of ſtupidity, either in not underſtanding the common and manifeſt te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents of the Church; or of perverſneſs and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, that knowing them would not own them; but by arguing from their variances that they were not all in all matters of Religion careful Collectors of the Churches traditions; Which, if you once admit, we cannot think to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude any thing from the Fathers till ſome third authority aſſure us, which of the many (for ought appears to us) of equal abilities
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169831:39"/>and zeal were the careful Collectors, which not; and in what particulars they were ſo, and in what not.</p>
               <p>To your ſecond ground, that they are ſincere Conveyers unto us of the traditions of the Church, I ſay, that to the juſt title of ſincere Conveyers, two conditions are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite: the one affirmative, that they ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver to us (with all their rights that is, clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, perſpicauity &amp; identitie of ſenſe as they received them) all the right traditions of the Church. And that the Fathers are not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have done this, may be inferred from what hath been ſaid before of their want of care and induſtry in collecting the Churches ſene concerning our affairs, matters being ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome right in the ſecond digeſtion which were not good in the firſt. The other is negative, that they ſhould not deliver any thing for a tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church univerſal, that was not rightly and evidently ſuch. That the Fathers were not Scrupulous in this point, my former inſtances I conceive have ſufficiently evinced. Wherein it is evident with what confidence, to doubtful, yea, and erroneous doctrines that themſelves effected, they ſet this preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded great ſeal of infallibility. Beleeve me, Couſin, that ſaying of St. <hi>Hierom, Ingenium ſuum facit Eccleſiae Sacramenta,</hi> belongs not onely unto <hi>Origen;</hi> it may without wrong be
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169831:39"/>extended to moſt of the Fathers that I have been acquainted with. And no marvel that they ſhould ſometimes in heat of diſpute be tranſported to vouch for tradition what was not, when ſo often they ſwerve from what was apparently the univerſal receptions of the Church, as hath been made evident by many examples. From which I do not infer that the Fathers had alwayes ſuch erroneous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefs as their words would many times import, but onely that it is likely that they (who in heat of diſpute, or for ſome ends which they thought very important, would recede in their expreſſions from the confeſt tradition of the Church in ſuch high conſtitutive points of Chriſtian Religion) would not be ſcrupulous in the like heats, or upon the like ends to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apply the ſeal of tradition to ſome points of leſſer importance. For though it appear a greater falſehood to ſet a ſeal ſurreptitiouſly where it belongs not, yet it is neerer to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion not to conforme to that Authority where the Royal ſeal is manifeſtly ſtamp'd. There hath enough been ſaid to manieſt that the Fathers (that would ſometimes thus licenſe themſelves, be the occaſion what it will, and the end how pious ſoever) cannot paſs for Candid or ſincere conveyers of all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches receptions unto us: and if leſs punctual in any, ſure likelieſt in our controverted do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169831:40"/>which rarely had they the occaſion to mention: but as ſerving to greater ends, there were ſo many circumſtances that might tempt and lead them from the exact punctual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of a ſincere conveyer, that I am not much ſcandalized at their prevarication.</p>
               <p>You ſhall finde that where <hi>Gregory Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Arienſis,</hi> ſaid, that the Father and the Son, according to our conceptions were two, but but one in <hi>Hypoſtaſis;</hi> St. <hi>Baſil, Ep.</hi> 64. <hi>p.</hi> 849. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. excuſes him, ſaying, that it was ſpoken <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and that being to perſwade a Gentile, he thought it not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be exact in his expreſſions; and that it may be convenient ſometimes to indulge a little, to the uſe and manner of thoſe one would perſwade, that they may not fly back from what is more neceſſary and ſeaſonable; by which means <hi>Gregory,</hi> ſaith he, may have let ſlip many expreſſions that Hereticks per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps will lay hold of for their advantage: like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe where <hi>Dionyſius Alexandrinus</hi> had ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Son the workmanſhip of the Father, as the ſhip to the ſhip-wright, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expreſſions that no Arian could mend; <hi>Athanaſius</hi> is ready with an Apologie for him, <hi>p.</hi> 551.552. <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>de Sent. Dyonis.</hi> They were ſaith he, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and are not to be taken maliciouſly.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:169831:40"/>
               <p>If that <hi>Thaumaturgus,</hi> and that other great pillar of the Church <hi>Dionyſius</hi> did licenſe themſelves ſo far as to let their expreſſions (by which we are to judge of them, not by what they reſerved in their hearts) ſwerve in ſo notorious a manner from the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent tradition of the Church, in ſuch a grand fundamental, were it not irrational in us to expect from them and the reſt a pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual tranſmiſſion of the Churches traditions in all ſuch petty points as moſt of ours, ſcarce ever touch'd upon by them, but in the way of thoſe important diſputes, which you ſee warm'd them even to ſuch great overſights? If thoſe two excellent and moſt zealous of the Fathers, <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and <hi>Baſil</hi> were ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in their excuſe, allowing them a liberty both for their policy and paſſion in diſpute to dally with a main tradition, were it not too unjuſt a rigour in us to brand them with the imputation of falſehood and ignorance; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, forſooth, they deliver us not with an exact fidelity the tradition of the Church in our queſtions, concerning which it is to be doubted, whether there was any general tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in the Church or no? I profeſs I am as far from laying ſo heavy an imputation upon them, either for their negligence herein or falſity, as I am from expecting ſuch a ſincere punctuallity, as you promiſe your ſelf from
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169831:41"/>them. Furthermore, beſides the heats, the artifice of Diſputes, and deſire of victory, which in conteſtations of great moment might eaſily through their humane frailty make them ſtrain a Point by the by in ſome article leſs dangerous, when from it they may draw con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions of great advantage in the main. And beſides that, as a great
<note n="*" place="margin">Arch. Biſhop of Canterb. Epiſt. dedic.</note> Prelate lately made the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, Men are apt to think that they can never run far enough from what they hate; and ſo by a very naturall motion runne upon the other extreame, as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that in deteſtation of <hi>Neſtorius</hi> would confound that hereſie by the recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Church, might eaſily overſhoot himſelf ſo farr, as to make the Church ſpeak for <hi>Eutiches</hi> in averſion from <hi>Arianiſm,</hi> make the Church ſpeak for <hi>Sabellius,</hi> and in profligation of the <hi>Maniches</hi> to ſhake hands with <hi>Pelagius,</hi> and ſo much more becauſe the danger could hardlier be foreſeen, they are likely to have tuned the voice of the Church, either to the Romiſh or Proteſtant Key, according as either was at the time moſt oppoſite to the Adverſarie they combated; Beſides all theſe, I am perſwaded that many of the Fathers held it a pious fraud to gain the ſubverſion of a great error by ſowing a little one, not foreſeeing how proceſs of time
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169831:41"/>might improve that to as conſiderable a mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude: Yea further I beleeve, and Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> implies little leſs, <hi>Ep.</hi> 50. <hi>ad Pamach. Com.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 136. that in the general the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers when they were in the Liſts, held it no matter of conſcience, either to affirm for the Churches receptions, ſome things that they did not think to be ſo, yea contrary to their knowledge; and to reject others that at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time they would have admitted, ſo it were conducible to their victory: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this be a greater, as being a more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full unfaithfulneſs then any other that I have remark'd in them, yet neither for this nor the reſt, dare I brand them with thoſe heavy imputations which you ſeem Jealouſs that I tend to: But ſince I finde that thoſe reverend and holy men do not ſtick to ſet the ſeal of tradition to conceits of their own, and other uncurrent doctrines, I do not fall preſently, as you implie one muſt do of conſequence, to lay to their charge impiety and profanation of the divineſt Averments. But rather ſince they make ſo bold with that ſeal, to believe that they did not repute it ſo ſacred as you ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, but farr inferior to proofs out of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and to be uſed freely as a <hi>Topick</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only when they wanted demonſtrations from thence; and indeed, throughout my ſlender reading, I have obſerved that when
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169831:42"/>they can produce the written word for their opinion, they do rarely inſiſt upon preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as pleading Lawyers fly then to preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents chiefly when they want a text for their cauſe; But whereas you ſay, the foule play would not have ſcaped their numerous adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries note, had they ſet the ſacred Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter to counterfeit Coine; I think ſo too. But what are we the wiſer if their notes ſcape ours, as needs they muſt, ſince of the nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous writings of their numerous adverſaries, this age I think hath ſcarce a number. The Governours of the Church in all times have made it one of their chief cares to ſmother their impious Libells, dictated, as Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> ſaies by the ſpirit of the devill: And however ſome do alledge, that ſuch ſuppreſſions make a cauſe ſuſpected, for my part I think it (if not abuſed) both a wiſe and Religious courſe, ſince the ſcandall and weakning of the weakers faith, which are ſo many, is much more to be conſidered and regarded, then the ſatisfying of the curioſity of the learned, which are ſo few; it fares with <hi>Sabellius,</hi> with <hi>Manicheus,</hi> with <hi>Porphirie</hi> and the reſt of the Heretiques, or enemies of Chriſt, that live only in the works of their Antagoniſts, as with <hi>Celſus</hi> in <hi>Origen,</hi> and with <hi>Arius</hi> in <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers whoſe confutations we are to thank; for all we know of their Arguments our Libraries
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169831:42"/>are juſt as well furniſhed with them as you may imagine ſome good <hi>Fraters</hi> cloſet in <hi>Spain,</hi> that hath the Inquiſitor for his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, is with the workes of <hi>Calvin,</hi> or <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> or as the world is likely to be provided of thoſe paſſages in the Fathers that make for them ſome ages hence, when time ſhall have worn out all Editions that are not according to the <hi>Index expurgatoricis,</hi> of which thoſe I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in my former Letter, <hi>Euſebius, Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> and Saint. <hi>Auſtin</hi> have not miſt their gentle wipe, though you ſay you have not met in either of them with any Article of Faith that you doe not moſt intirely aſſent unto. For my part, I doe not know what you underſtand by an Article of Faith; but I am ſure I have ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of St. <hi>Auſtin [of the neceſſity of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens partaking of the Euchariſt]</hi> an Article in this diſcourſe, which 'tis evident he held as an Article both of neceſſary faith and practice, wherein I believe you will refuſe to joyne with him. As for <hi>Epiphanius</hi> his over-ſights, I referre you onely to the Jeſuit <hi>Petavius,</hi> and for <hi>Euſebius</hi> to Cardinall <hi>Perron,</hi> who caſts upon him a trifling aſperſion but of Arrianiſm: or if his authority ſuffice not, let <hi>Jerome</hi> (<hi>Ep.</hi> 65. <hi>ad Pamach. &amp; Oc.</hi>) be heard, who gives him this good teſtimony, <hi>Impietatis Arrii apertiſſimus propugnator eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to your third and laſt ground, That
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169831:43"/>the traditions of the Church are infallible: I ſay, that in part we agree in this point; for I am perſwaded that no man in his right wits will ever deny the firmeſt aſſent he hath about him to traditions of the nature which you Character doctrines taught by Chriſt to his Apoſtles, and by them preached through the world, and then again delivered to the enſuing ages by them that had theſe points inculcated in their hearts by the Apoſtles, &amp; in this manner with care, and every where han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded over from age to age, which upon parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular occaſions the Fathers uſed to ſumme up and produce againſt innovators that would make breaches upon the ancient and generally received faith of the Church-Traditions of this nature: Doctrines thus delivered, I ſay, we agree to be derived from infallible Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as well as the Scriptures; and it is indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent unto me, whether I receive the waters of life from the Springs themſelves, from the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ciſternes and conſerves into which they did immediarly flow, or elſe conveyed through Aquiducts at ſixteen hundred yeares diſtance, ſo I be certain of the ſtanchneſſe and purity of the pipes. That ſuch traditions, and ſo exactly conveyed there are in the Church, and to which is due, as to the Scripture, from every prudent man (how ever a Sophiſter may ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill) the ſtrongeſt aſſent of his ſoule; we like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:169831:43"/>both agree, ſuch are thoſe fore-named grand fundamentals of Chriſtianity; we agree further, that by tradition we are (as you ſay) plainly, fully, and practifically taught how to underſtand Scripture, I mean, in thoſe Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals. And much more muſt I agree with you, that the buſineſſe and errand of tradition is to deliver it ſo unto us, ſince for my part I hold, that thoſe dignifying circumſtances (by which tradition may rightly pretend to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible) belong onely to ſuch doctrines as are either plainly, or by neceſſary conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces deducibly coucht in Scripture: in regard of which deductions we agree further, that it cannot be denied, but that it is (as you ſay) an eaſier and better rule to guide our underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in the affairs of religion, to uſe the help of ſuch traditions, then to reſort for that end unto Scriptures alone: as to read a book wherein there are difficulties, with a judicious comment, is likely to be more profitable, then onely to peruſe the ſingle Text. And this laſt I aſſent unto, without admitting of the ſuppoſition upon which you inferre it, to wit, that there can by tradition be had a compleat knowledge of all that Chriſt taught. All this we are of accord in; but what can you infer from hence to the advantage of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> cauſe, ſince I peremptorily deny that there is ſuch a qualified tradition really belonging to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169831:44"/>any Tenent of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> diſapprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by us, or that ſeale with thoſe quarterings and dignifyings wherewith you blazon it, ſet by any of the primitive Fathers (which yet were no ſufficient warrant) to any doctrine that doth ſo much as border upon our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes; ſince then I am ſure you directed that part of your Letter to the ſame purpoſe that the reſt, I muſt anſwer what I conceive it tends to, as well as what directly your words beare. And as I have profeſt wherein we agree; ſo now I muſt ſet down in what and why we dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; concerning theſe particulars of Tradition and Scripture, There are two principall poynts wherein I diſſent from you: Firſt, that in the generall you conceive all Traditions of the Church whatſoever infallible. Secondly, that you hold the Scripture to be no compleat body of Faith, and therefore that we are to give tradition much the preheminency in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning the tenour of ours. For the firſt, namely, that all the traditions of the Church are infallible, I could by one demand (of which is that Church whoſe traditions are infallible) either bring you to our confeſſion that the true Church is to be known meerly by its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to Scripture in belief and practice, or elſe into a circle whilſt you are forc'd to prove the truth and infallibility of the Church, by her conſtant reception of thoſe true and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169831:44"/>traditions, whoſe truth and infallibility you are at the ſame time proving by the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches conſtant receiving them. But I paſſe it by, becauſe I would not ſeeme to argue in any wiſe captiouſly; and alſo for that Mr. <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingworth</hi> hath already excellently laid open all the intricaſies of this labyrinth. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore taking the preſent <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church for that you mean, I proceed to anſwer your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, wherby in your Letter to the Vicoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of <hi>P.</hi> to which you referre me, you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to prove all doctrines of the Church received or delivered by way of tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, infallible: the chiefe that I finde are in the 12, and 13. concluſions, as you call them, of that treatiſe; where firſt, for proof of your aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions, that no falſe doctrine of Faith what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever can be admitted or creep into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, you ſay, that whatſoever the preſent Church beleeveth, as a propoſition of faith, is upon this ground, that Chriſt taught it as ſuch unto the Church he planted himſelf; a ſpecial good ground, and that will ſoon end all controverſies in this matter, if the ground ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be well grounded; and that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which you ſuppoſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Catholick, do never admit any doctrine of Faith but upon that ground. But firſt, the ground can never be made good, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever of Faith the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teacheth
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169831:45"/>was <hi>ab initio</hi> ſo taught by Chriſt himſelf. And ſecondly, I beleeve that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelf doth not alwayes in all that ſhe teaches for a tradition of Faith, ſuppoſe that Chriſt himſelf did teach the ſame; for this latter part, I am better perſwaded of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> then to think that ſhe will ſo much as pretend it, for all her doctrines, as for example, that of communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting onely in the bread, is a tradition, for you will not I ſuppoſe vouch Scripture for it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you mean to apply to it Chriſt's prayer that the Cup might be removed; it is a traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Faith, yea, and I think I may ſay of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary faith, for unleſs the Communicants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve their partaking ſufficient, it muſt needs make that great Sacrament of the Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual; and yet I do not think that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or ſcarce any Jeſuite for her, will have the confidence to pretend that Chriſt himſelf taught the mutilation, or the belief of one Elements ſufficiency, ſince the contrary practiſe and belief is ſo evident for many ages after Chriſt; and it is ſo eaſie to diſcover the very drie root it ſelf, of the cuſtome to with-hold the cup from the people; The like may be ſaid of other doctrines; Now for proof of the ground it ſelf, that all do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Faith whatſoever admitted in the preſent Church, were ſo taught by Chriſt to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169831:45"/>the Church which he planted himſelf; you Alledge this argument: The reaſon why the preſent Church beleeveth any propoſition to be of Faith, is, becauſe the immediate prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Church of the age before delivered it unto her for ſuch, and ſo you may drive it on (ſay you) from age to age until you come to the Apoſtles and Chriſt; an eaſie progreſs; and which, if you remember Mr. <hi>White</hi> much inſiſted upon at that time when Mr. <hi>Chilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> did me the favour to give him a mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for conference at your lodging; although I ſet a great value upon that Gentlemans lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and fair way of diſputation; yet I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs his argument hath often made me ſmile; it did ſo bring into my head that gallant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of <hi>Charles Thynnes,</hi> wherewith all you once made me very merry, by which he undertook to demonſtrate, that ſurely in the world there might be a man ſo diſpoſed as (having a good riſe, and with a convenient ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer) to leap at once from <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Rome;</hi> for (ſaid he) Bring me the beſt Jumper you know, and is it not likely that there may be another that you know not, ſo active as to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jump him a foot; let him be brought, I hope you will not deny but he may be out-jumpt an Inch: &amp; ſo by inches &amp; ſtraws-breadths of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaping one another, why not to a thouſand miles? I dare ſay, that Mr. <hi>Hooper</hi> was better
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169831:46"/>ſatisfied of the corruption of times in his pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree from King <hi>Peppin,</hi> then I was by that logick of the incorruption of times in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of all Romiſh Doctrines from Chriſt; nor am I yet better ſatisfied, though I confeſs by your dwelling on the ſame Argument, I ſee plainly, that what may be liable to much ſlighting, propoſed by one man, may be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with ſuch weight and authority from another, as though it convince not, yet to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a ſerious pondering and diſcuſſion; the ſcope of your reaſoning, as I underſtand it, is this deduction <hi>ad Impoſſibile:</hi> If the preſent Church (ſay you) hold a Doctrine of Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is becauſe all they of the precedent ſo held it and delivered it; and the reaſon of the preceding Churches holding it ſo, is the ſame relative to all thoſe of the next before, and ſo on till you come to the firſt Age of the Church: Now this being ſo, there cannot be admitted (ſay you) unto the avowed channell of the Church, any corrupt Rivolet of erroneous Doctrine, unleſs all they of one Age conſpire in an untruth to deceive poſterity, which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. This latter Aſſertion, which I muſt confeſs to be ſtrangely jarring to my ſenſe, is built upon a ſuppoſition of the former, which is it ſelf of great ambiguity: For, beſides that as I ſaid formerly, I doe not think but that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth receive ſome unwritten
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169831:46"/>doctrines for which ſhe dares not pretend to ſo ancient a pedigree, as to have been handed down to her from the Primitive Church that Chriſt himſelf hath planted; I would fain know when the preſent Church, as you ſay, holds a thing for ſuch, becauſe (all they) of the precedent age in Chriſts Church delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it to them for ſuch, what is underſtood by Your (all they) of the Catholick Church in the age precedent; by (all they) cannot be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended here, what you ſay in your eleventh concluſion, namely, that you mean the whole Congregation of the faithful, ſpread through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole world, for it is a far more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent impoſſibility, then what you drive unto, that the whole congregation of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful throughout the world in one age ſhould confer with and teach the whole congregation of the faithful throughout the world in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: If it be underſtood by (all they) all the Doctors and Governors of one age, to all the faithful throughout the whole world of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; I think you will finde that likewiſe to border upon impoſſibilitie.</p>
               <p>By, All they, then, as I conceive muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood all the Doctors and Governors of the Church in one age, to all the Doctors and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors of the Church in another; and from them the Doctrines ſpred among the whole multitudes of the faithful, are ſaid to be the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169831:47"/>traditions of the Catholick Church: Now this is ſo narrow a confinement of univerſallity to the mouthes of the Doctors or Governors of a preſent Church, that I think it no impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity for all thoſe that have declared themſelves in ſome point, in ſome age, to have agreed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether on the teaching of ſomewhat more then was true, or at leaſt ſuch a major part of them, as the diſſentors may well have bin overborn or ſuppreſt; ſo that the doctrine may with a ſucceeding age, have paſt for a tradition generally agreed on; and to ſuch a conſpiracy, methinks, they might have been drawn by appearances of good, as well as through ill ends: As for Example. The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors conceiving that a great reſtraint might be laid upon ill-livers by Auricular confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (the apprehenſion of a ſenſible witneſſe being moſt lively unto them) might have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plotted to teach the neceſſity of it to the multitude for an univerſal tradition, which perhaps they knew not to have been ſuch: and ſo in other points, as the good or danger might appear more or leſs to the Governors of the Church: ſo likewiſe for worſe ends, in point of the Popes Supremacy, it being a Doctrine ſo eſſential to the Monarchy of the Church; I beleeve it far from impoſſible, that in ſome age all the Doctors of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſhall be heard, may reſolve to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169831:47"/>teach it to their ſeveral Congregations, for univerſal tradition, ſince the major part, as a Pope (<hi>Aeneas Sylvius</hi>) himſelf confeſſeth, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms that the Pope is above Councels; becauſe he hath ſo many Biſhopricks to beſtow, the Councels have none; beſides, if your (All they) of a precedent Church of Chriſt, inſtructing the preſent, be reduced to ſo few as the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, that are heard deliver their mindes in any one age, The natural Argument by which you would prove the impoſſibility of a conſpiracy in an untruth, will fall to the ground, ſince that is built upon a ſuppoſition, that thoſe general traditions which cannot be erroneous, becauſe of Humane natures, love of truth are delivered by ſuch a multitude of men as contain in them all the variety of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions and affections incident to the nature of man, which I doubt much whether it can truly be affirmed of all the Chriſtians of the world; I am ſure it cannot of the poor num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Doctors and Governors in any one age among them: But to let this ſuppoſition paſs, ſuppoſing that the preſent Church under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands what is meant by (All they) of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding, though I do not; and that all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent receives, ſhe receives as delivered to her by all thoſe of the preceding age: let us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine a little that which you inferr upon it, to wit, That this being ſo, no falſe propoſition
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169831:48"/>of faith, nay (as you ſay afterwards) no falſe doctrine whatſoever can be admitted into the Church in any age, unleſs they of that age do unanimouſly conſpire to deceive their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and youngers, in telling them they were taught by their Fathers, what indeed they were not; That this is not impoſſible, ſince only the Doctors &amp; Paſtors of the Church are to be underſtood by (All they) hath been alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhown: But is there no other way, ſay you, but this for falſhood to creep into the Church? Truely (me-thinks) on the contrary it is with error and neceſſary truths, in the body Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick, as with life and death in the body natural; And as there is onely one way for life to enter at, but a thouſand gates for death, ſo for neceſſary truths there is but one ordinary avenne to the Church, namely by Scripture read or taught, but for error to get in at a thouſand paſſages, without ſuppoſing ſuch a general conſpiracie: For though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times when an error hath had a long Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, we cannot point directly at the ſpring, yet are we ne're a whit leſs certain that it had an entrance, becauſe we know not at which doore; <hi>Nilus</hi> hath a head, though <hi>Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> cannot ſay directly where it is: And lines many times that at firſt appear parallels to the eie, by that time they have been length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a great while, prove apparently uneven,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169831:48"/>though no man can aſſigne the point whereat the deflexion began. The doctrine of the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaſts,</hi> a doctrine which if any other ſurely that may well be ſaid to have been a generally received tenent of the Church univerſal for ſome ages, ſince in the whole Church for above 250. years after Chriſt, there appears not in that point one diſſenting vote, till <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> oppos'd it; An error 'tis true, and yet I hope you will not be ſo uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as to accuſe all the ancient Fathers of the ſecond Centenary that they complotted to deceive poſterity by teaching them a falſhood for Apoſtolique tradition, you are more favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to them then ſo, in the laſt part of the Letter, where you your ſelf diſcover a way how without conſpiracy, this error, and ſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may have overſpread the Church by the Authority of one man delivering it for a whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper of the Apoſtles; And truly Couſin, what ever elſe may be ſaid more probable in the particular, I am confident 'tis moſt true in the general, that the worke is eaſie from one man of credits Aſſeveration, to poſſeſs vaſt Multitudes with firme perſwaſions of a falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; and more in matters of Religion then in civil things, ſince in thoſe this <hi>pium credere</hi> prevailes much, and moſt will rather take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on truſt what many affirm, and they diſcern no ill in, then put themſelves to the oft-times
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169831:49"/>endleſs troubles of examining: Credulity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo eaſie and natural, Diſproving ſo diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult.</p>
               <p>I warrant you the Common Faith of <hi>Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> Aſcent into Heaven, would have had up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your grounds as rational aſſertours in the State of <hi>Rome,</hi> as any tradition by us queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned at this day in the ſea of <hi>Rome:</hi> See in that politique invention of <hi>Julius Proclus,</hi> what power the imagined pietie of one man hath to make a fiction paſs for an Epidemicall veritie, which as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſayes, <hi>Apol. cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Ab uno aliquando principe exorta, exinde in traduces linguarum, &amp; aurium ſerpat, &amp; ita modici ſeminis vitium, caetera rumoris ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurat, ut nemo recogitet num primum illud os mendatium ſeminaverit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Jewes, a much more numerous multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude heretofore, and ſtill I think equal in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to any Chriſtian Church of one denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, were the moſt Religious, the moſt ſcrupulous conſervators of unwritten truths in their <hi>Cabala.</hi> And yet what an error poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes the whole Nation, and did ſo long before the curſe fell upon them, concerning their Meſſias; whoſe coming long before Chriſt, and ſince, they all expected and do expect in a temporal kingdome, of which they did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive, and do continue to poſteritie the hopes by Univerſal tradition; or if you will ſay that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169831:49"/>they build the doctrine, not upon tradition but Scripture; yet I am ſure you cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie but that they continue the interpretation of Scripture that way by tradition, which comes all to one.</p>
               <p>Did you grant the poſſibility of a Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes Conſpiracie, I am ſure you would denie it in this, which is confeſtly the point upon which all of them agree, that their ſupreme felicitie depended.</p>
               <p>It would paſs for a very fallacious reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to drive up this belief to the Patriarkes, and ſo conclude it infallible, becauſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent age received it for a tradition from the preceding; and that from the <hi>Antepenul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time</hi> and ſo forward: Or becauſe the inſtant where the error was admitted amongſt them cannot <hi>Digito monſtrari &amp; dicere hic eſt.</hi> For truly Couſin, partly through a natural deſire in all men, that others ſhould think as they do, or do what they think convenient (from whence there ſprings an aptneſs in the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, to applie to their opinions the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Authorities they can deviſe, whether they do juſtly belong unto them or no) and partly through an aptneſs of the ignorant (which are the greateſt part of Auditours) to ſwallow more, and retain better the words, and the outward literal part of what is taught them, then either to examine or hold faſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169831:50"/>and inward ſenſe; It may well happen that multitudes may mumble the ſhell, when a few have the kernell; and looking ſuperficially only upon the outward ſtamp, toſs up and down for currant among them counterfeit oft-times and Adulterate Coine; The miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take is ordinary, and the propagation of the error eaſie; for inſtance ſake, in the doctrine of praying for the dead, many of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Church, who believed that all the ſouls of the departed were kept in certain receptacles untill the general reſurrection, conceiving that prayer for the beatitude of the dead, came all to one with praying for the haſtening of Chriſts Kingdome, might teach it others, thinking, it no prophanation of prayer to imploy that holy Act even where we know it cannot availe, ſince Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf prayed to have the bitter Cup of his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on removed; and all the Doctours gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally holding ſuch prayers a convenient te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of charity in the living, whether they were Commemorative, Euchariſticall, or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicatorie, eaſily might the practice paſs into a common doctrine.</p>
               <p>Now the word Neceſſarie being often uſed for Convenient (as it had need) ſince under a leſs pretenſion then Neceſſarie, it is hard impoſing new duties upon the multitude; And the ſtep being ſo eaſie, though ſo great
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:169831:50"/>from neceſſarie to abſolutely neceſſary, 'tis no marvaile that all or moſt of the Paſtors ſhould have delivered it for ſuch to their Flockes, and applied to it the ſeale of moſt Authority with the multitudes, Tradition; and ſo they have ſwallowed that according to the expreſſion for a neceſſary duty, and given it the generall voague of ſuch in the Church, which was farre from being truly ſo in its firſt, and after ſo long a progreſſe untraceable originals.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe of Chriſts deſcent into Hell, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which I ſuppoſe all antiquity agrees in the ſhell of the Article, <hi>Deſcendit ad Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros</hi> (though <hi>Ruffinus</hi> [<hi>in Symb.</hi>] ſays it was left out of the Symbole of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) few of the Fathers in the kernell, or inward ſenſe, that is, what was underſtood by <hi>Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</hi> and how, and why Chriſt deſcended thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Some taking the <hi>Inferi</hi> to be a part of Hel, others underſtanding it with a little more colour of reaſon, that reſting place called <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams Boſome,</hi> and a part of Heaven. Some thinking, and rightly, as I conceive, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended virtually onely to triumph over the damned. Others, that locally, yea ſo farre as to preach in hell, and convert there; ſuch was the extravagant opinion of <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> [<hi>Strom. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>p:</hi> 639.] one of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedeſt of the pack, but all agreeing I ſay, in
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169831:51"/>this outſide, <hi>Deſcendit ad Inferos,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. No marvell that the more groſſe and literall ſenſe ſhould be ſwallowed by the multitude, and gain the name (though an errour) of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reception, handed to them from their Forefathers: ſo that it may be collected out of what hath been ſaid, that falſhoods may creep into the Church either by want of exact fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in the Teachers (which want may be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall when the collaterall conſiderations are generall, and the poynts themſelves not thought ſo important as others they ſerve to:) Or by the frequent miſapprehenſion of the teached, the matter often taking poſſeſſion of them, when the manner of the doctrine uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moſt conſiderable, is either let ſlip or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted, or elſe by leiſurable, yea and at firſt inſenſible miſtakes either in Teachers or Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which notwithſtanding in long progreſs of time grow manifeſt and vaſt, like the eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bings and flowings of the Sea, which at the end of ſome houres make ſo great a difference, when at the brink no man can perceive how much ground each wave doth gain or loſe: What then ſhall thoſe diſcern that look upon the ſeverall billows at a remote and dazzeling diſtance? Nor can your arguments taken from humane Natures prime appetence of Truth, ſerve to conclude an infallibility in whatſoever ſhal be imbrac'd for a truth by a vaſt multitude
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:169831:51"/>of men of variety of natures, diſpoſitions and intereſts.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe no number whatſoever of Individuals, but that which makes up the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall, can be conſidered as other then a part, wheras your argument is not colourably appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to leſſe then the whole. It is the infruſtrable appetence of truth (an appropriate of humane nature in the generall) that you inſiſt upon, which is not made vain by any multitudes (which how great ſoever is ſtill but a part) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining of a falſhood.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe if we admit of your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, it will conclude for Heretickes once grown numerous, as the <hi>Arrians</hi> were, as well as for the beſt Catholickes, ſince naturall Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petences are not to be ſuppoſ'd more fruſtrate in the one then in the other:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lactantius Divin. Inſt. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.</note> 
                  <hi>An boni noſtri qualitas ex populi poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us pendebit erroribus quam ex con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia noſtra &amp; judicio Dei.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, becauſe though I grant your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, I am never a whit the ſurer of truth, where I finde many profeſſors of a doctrine held as by tradition, ſince the prime naturall appetence of truth (whence you draw your ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiocination) is to the knowledge of truth, not the teaching of it. Now in our queſtion this is as much or more requiſite in the deliverers, then the other in the receivers, ſince they
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169831:52"/>look no further then the hands they had it from, and to hold faſt in truth what they preſented them for ſuch, and for ſo conveyed by their preceders to them.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, your argumentation cannot be uſefull, becauſe you extend it only to prove that multitudes cannot agree together, on an untruth to complot it; whereas to overthrow your imagined infallibility, it is enough that they agree in, or to an untruth to believe it; Between which two there is ſo great a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that I think the firſt very improbable, the other very frequent: Nay farther, I do conceive the very frequencie and (if I may ſo ſay) aptneſs in Individuals, whether few or many (which makes a multitude) to be led into errors, to reſult from mans natural af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to truth, which is ſuch and ſo tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting, that we are glad to embrace and hug the very ſhadowes of it; And being rarely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in our imperfect and depreſt condition here, to arive to a ſolid enjoyment of that prime eſſence of Intellectual delight, we grow fond of the appearances, and cleave cloſe to what is like it. Mans affection to this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent, expreſſing it ſelf after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that it uſually doth to the other prime fellow appetence of our Nature (good) which our ſoul here below, interially and naturally aims at in all its purſuances: But the onely
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:169831:52"/>true good being too farr elevated for it to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to a full enjoyment thereof, whilſt it beares the clogg of fleſh upon it, our ardor directs it ſelf to what we think of neareſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivation from it. But alas, we miſſe even of that, and embrace falſe ſhadowes for it, eaſily conceiting any thing the ſame that's but clad like unto what we love, whilſt almoſt all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind courts, purſues and enjoyes what's ill, yet ſeldome or never, but <hi>ſub ratione boni.</hi> And thus by eaſily believing what we fain would have, by a naturall paſſion both to good and truth, we are betraid to a miſtaking credulity in both.</p>
               <p>Thus Couſin, I have preſumed to give you an Anſwer in my immethodical and unpolliſht way, to what I finde repugnant to my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, in the diſcourſe to which you refer'd me for proofe of infallibilitie in all the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> To diſcuſſe that learned and eloquent Diſcourſe through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, in any correſpondency to its weight and beauty, belongs I conſeſſe to farre greater emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence then I have vanity to aim at. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what I have ventured upon, hath been onely to ſhew you, that although I am in the higheſt meaſure delighted, yea even raviſhed with that excellent piece, I am nothing a paid therewith in this particular; which may ſerve for an argument, that goodneſſe many times
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169831:53"/>delights the ſoul in ſpite of truth, and ſo proves a tranſcendent above it. Now that the falli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and conſequently the inſufficiency of your rule of faith, tradition, hath been made appeare, it will be fit to vindicate the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of that rule which we relie upon. In which work the firſt hinderance that I meet with is this objection of yours, That the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular books of Scripture were written for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther particular ends, and not to give us a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat body of faith.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, that if by particular books of Scripture you underſtand each book a part, ſevered from its relation to the whole, I then agree with you, that every particular book was no more intended for a compleat body of Faith, then every particular Chapter for a compleat body of the book, or then a Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow or a Door, to be a compleat body of a Houſe; but as the one was deſigned to give entrance, the other light to ſome room or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Ediſice; ſo the ſeveral books of Scripture were written; ſome to give entrance to Chriſtianity; ſome to illuſtrate dark pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the whole; ſome to inform us of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of fact, that we might underſtand in what chiefly to praiſe God; ſome to diſcipline us in matters of practice, that we might know how aptlieſt to ſerve and pleaſe him: And others to inſtruct us in matter of belief, that we might
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:169831:53"/>learn to relie upon him. But on the other ſide, if you remit the leaſt of this abſtract and Independent conſideration of the particular books of Scripture: I muſt then profeſs that I ſtedfaſtly beleeve that they were all deſigned to this chief and primary end of compoſing that compleat body of Faith, whereon Chriſts perfect Church ſhould be built as certainly as ſo many ſeveral parts of a building having each a particular end, beſides of their erecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are yet in the general and main intention all deſtin'd to the making up of one compleat and intire Fabrick; yea further, (without urging the compariſon till it halt) I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that as the Maſter Architect having an Idaea form'd of the whole, directs many a part to the perfection of that, when the ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate workman that frames it thinks of nothing farther then of the peice he is in hand with: So oftentimes the Almighty Architect, when his Miniſters perhaps never look'd further then that ſervice in particular, wherein they were imployed, ſome perhaps in a Goſpel, in an Epiſtle ſome; he by his infinite Wiſdom directed each particular to the making up of the whole and compleat body and rule of Faith, the written Word; which by his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable providence he hath, and will I am conſident ever preſerve intire and uncorrupt in all parts neceſſary to its own perfection
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:169831:54"/>and harmony, and to mans eternal ſafety and direction: Inſomuch, that I cannot but think it at the beſt loſs of time, to be ſolicitous after any other rule; and irreverence, if not impiety, to queſtion the ſufficiency of this. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my opinion is little conſiderable with one of ſo far a better Judgment, take in this Point the Opinion of the Fathers, which you ſo much relie upon. To begin with <hi>Tertullian,</hi> theſe are the laſt words of his 22. Chapter againſt <hi>Hermogines, Scriptum eſſe doceat</hi> Hermogenis <hi>officina:</hi> If it be not written (ſaith he) let him fear the Woe deſtin'd to ſuch as ſhall adde or take away. Can any thing be inferred more rightly then from this paſſage, the ſufficiency of Scripture, and the ſuperfluity of any other rule. But take yet ſomewhat more direct from
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Oratio ad Gentiles.</hi> towards the beginning.</note> 
                  <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> The holy, and from God inſpired Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures (ſaith he) are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of themſelves ſufficient to the diſcovery of truth. I appeal to St <hi>Baſil</hi> himſelf, of all the Fathers the greateſt attributer to Tradition in all things wherein regard is juſtly due unto it. Hear what he ſayes, handling a point wherein Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture (I think) is as dark as in any neceſſary one whatſoever; I mean that of the Trinity: Believe what's writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, (ſaith
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hom.</hi> 29. <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Calum. ſtan. Trin. page</hi> 623.</note> he) what is not written, ſeek not. And in another place, It
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:169831:54"/>is a manifeſt falling from the Faith (ſayes
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>De vera ac Pia ſide, page</hi> 251.</note> he) and an argument of Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, either to reject any of thoſe things that are written, or to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce any that are not of the written. And laſtly, to ſum up all that can be ſaid by a Proteſtant, in one ſentence of a Father of greateſt Learning and authority: Liſten but to St. <hi>Auguſtine, De doctrina Chriſtian. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>In its quae appertè in Scriptura poſitaſunt inveniuntur illa omnia quae continent fidem moreſque vivendi.</hi> He had need be a confident Sophiſter, that would undertake to evade theſe Authorities; but yet if they may not be admitted, let Scripture be heard for it ſelf: It is a priviledge and preeminence ſolely peculiar to that ſacred Volume to be Witneſs, Advocate and Judge in its own cauſe. Surely the Spirit ſpake in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he told <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> That holy Writ <hi>was able to make him wiſe unto ſalvation,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>in fine.</hi> And when numbring up almoſt all the particular parts that can be required to the compleat In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of a Chriſtian, he concludes, that in theſe by Scripture the man of God <hi>is made perfect, and fitted to every good work.</hi> And I am confident by the ſame Spirit he ſpake his own minde, when he ſpake ours ſo directly to the <hi>Corinthians, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t dicſatis in nobis ſupra id quod ſcriptum eſt non ſapere, Epiſt.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:169831:55"/>Where by the way it is to be noted, that the Apoſtle applies this doctrine as an Antidote to that very inconvenience which I have heard ſome Papiſts object againſt the reliance on the ſearch and uſe of Scripture, namely that by it thoſe of greater capacity were lkely to be blown up, and to glory in their clearer diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over weaker, whereas the guidance of the Church and Tradition was equaller to all. To this I ſay, 'tis worth obſerving what he delivers as it were by way of reaſon, for the contrary Doctrine, to wit of confining our ſelves to Scripture, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>I profeſs Conſin, that theſe and many other paſſages of Scripture which for brevities ſake I note only in the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut. cap.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; cap.</hi> 12. <hi>Epiſt. ad Gal. cap.</hi> 1.</note> Margent, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce to me in as clear a ſenſe as may be the ſufficiencie of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and ſuperſluity of relying on tradition for a rule of faith. And yet I ſweare I am none of thoſe of whom St. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>p.</hi> 621. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>How they may ſound, or what other ſenſe they may bear to you I know not, ſince now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes Gods Word proves to men of divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, as the Apoſtles language, when the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:169831:55"/>devided tongues had ſat upon them in Dr.
<note n="*" place="margin">This was likewiſe the fantaſtique o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the Authour of the book <hi>de Spiritu ſancto,</hi> fathered upon <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Alabaſters</hi> conceit to ſeverall Nations at one and the ſame time, <hi>Hebrew</hi> to the <hi>Jew,</hi> pure <hi>Greek</hi> to the <hi>Athenian,</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> to the <hi>Roman.</hi> Laſtly, if the Fathers Teſtimonie may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, they being of an uncertain Authority, nor Scripture ſwey, as being of an uncertain ſence, let common reaſon be heard in the cauſe, which for as much as I can judge of, it is as ſtrong for the ſufficiencie of Scripture (that is, its containing all points ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to ſalvation) as any prudent man need require for warrant of his belief. It is agreed upon by all ſides, that Man being ordained to a ſupernatural end, nature is not ſufficient to lead him thither, but that he muſt have ſome meanes above it, and proportionate to the end, ſuch as may either ſhew him the way, if he can diſcern, or lead him in it if he be blind, or which is happieſt and ſureſt of all, both inſtruct and conduct him in it. This laſt kinde of guidance, it were preſumption for man to claim, however Gods grace may afford it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome. The ſecond, it were ſtupidity for all to expect, however ſome have little hopes without it; And therefore it is the firſt that belongs to man in generall; that is a directory to all thoſe pathes and windings, without the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169831:56"/>knowledge of which he cannot arrive to his primary end; And by the knowledge of which he may, and is reſponſible himſelf if he do not follow the direction; which if God ſhould withhold from us, although I could not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with ſome to apply to his Juſtice that of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s requiring brick where he gives no ſtraw, nor to pronounce it a ſtain to his goodneſſe, ſhould he condemn us for miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the way, when he gave us no Map of the Countrey, ſince to a life actually forfeited as all mans was in <hi>Adam,</hi> the leaſt reprieve is a grace, a grace to be let row in the Gallies; to him that the Gallowes expected; A grace to take out of the ditch, a man that put out his own eyes, though you leave him to grope out the reſt of his journey with perpetuall hazards of falling in againe: I ſay, though I dare not in this caſe pronounce the with-holding a directory from us, inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with his juſtice, wiſdome or goodneſſe, yet truly I think you will yeeld, the man hath not ſo fitting a belief of Gods mercy &amp; wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as he ought, who conceives that he would ſuffer thoſe to periſh for want of ſuch a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary directory, for whoſe ſake he gave up his own Son to death. Now to ſuppoſe ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory from God, and to think it defective, is again to fall into undue thoughts, either of his mercy or of his power; nay, it is to deſtroy
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:169831:56"/>what you do ſuppoſe, ſince the omiſſion of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing abſolutely neceſſary in a direction, makes the direction none.</p>
               <p>This concluſion then I may ſafely draw, and I doubt not but with your conſent, that the Supernatural Directorie and rule whereby we are through Gods grace and mercy to be inſtructed in the way to our ſupernatural end, muſt needs be compleat and ſufficient in all parts abſolutely neceſſary to that end. It on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remains then to ſhew which is that rule and directory ſufficient and compleat in all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry parts: Now as in a journey, directions of the way, how ſufficient, how exact ſoever, will little advance you; unleſs you beleeve them, or the knowledge of the way, unleſs you have legs to go, or ſomewhat elſe to carry you: ſo in our Souls progreſs to beatitude, it muſt have reliance and its inſtruments of gradation too, which is Faith, the ſtrongeſt <hi>vehiculum</hi> of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity to Divinity.</p>
               <p>Now as I ſaid before, that the means muſt be proportionate to the end, ſo it is certain that the way, &amp; the Organs by which we move in it, muſt be proportionate one to another, or we ſhall never arrive at our end: As that let all other things be never ſo well fitted, yet if our way muſt be thorow the Air or the Sea, good legs or directions will little avail us. The Organ then of our motion to Heaven being
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:169831:57"/>Faith, and that Faith the ſtrongeſt aſſent of our ſouls; the ground upon which it muſt march ought to be no leſs folid then infallibility, ſince the ſtrongeſt Aſſent cannot be given but upon the ſtrongeſt inducement: Foraſmuch then as particular Tradition, that is the unanimous teſtimony of any Church, of what numerous parts ſoever, hath been already concluded fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible and univerſal Tradition, is, as it were, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incident with Scripture, being only, (as <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> ſayes, <hi>Strom. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 679.) as it were, an unwritten Tranſcript of that in mens hearts, and gives atteſtation to no materiall Object of Faith, but what is deducible thence. It follows, That Scripture is the ground propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by unqueſtionable infallibity to Faith, as correſpondent likewiſe in all things elſe, both to the goodnes of <hi>God</hi> that gives the directory &amp; to our neceſſities that are to follow it. The ſufficiency and perfection of Scripture having been ſhewed, and likewiſe the defectibility of that kinde of Tradition for whoſe Authority you labour; The preferring of this latter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the firſt in governing the Tenure of our Faith, is of conſequence ſuch an error as I am ſorry ſhould be countenanced by your conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing in it. But becauſe the precedency which you give to the Churches Tradition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Scripture, is pretended due upon another ground alſo, which I have yet ſpoke little un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to:
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169831:57"/>give me leave to ſay ſomewhat to that. You lay Obſcurity to the charge of Scripture; That Articles of Faith are not there ſo plainly expreſt, that every body can underſtand them. If it were ſo, truely the Laytie of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is much obliged to it, for eaſing them of the trouble of reading what is unintelligible unto them; but little beholding unto S. <hi>John,</hi> for paſſing for a precept of Chriſt's, <hi>Search the Scriptures.</hi> But how ſhall they take it now, foraſmuch as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to your Aſſertion, is a manifeſt Corollary to the proof of Scriptures ſufficiencie and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? the compleatneſs of a Rule or Directory conſiſting as well in its Evidence, as its Fulneſs; and muſt need Interpretation, as little as Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Yet let us grant your ſuppoſition a while. Scripture is obſcure, you ſay. What follows? Tradition is to be preferred. Tradition then is eaſier; Tradition is clear, ſay you, to the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar. I ſhould rather think Tradition impoſſible to be learn'd, ſince Man can ſpeak but with a few; and millions muſt make up that; unleſs you bring all lines that can be drawn from the Circumference, into a Centrical point, the Pope. But you are too much a friend to the Doctors of the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> to do that. Beſides, if you do ſo, the difficulty will ſtill remain: For here the Rule in Geometry will not hold. The lines drawn back from the Centre to the Circumference, are not equal. Men are not all at an equal diſtance
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:169831:58"/>from him; all cannot hear him: How ſhall the Vulgar underſtand him? By their Ghoſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? You will not attribute to private men a clearer, fuller, and evidenter capacity to inſtruct, then the whole Body of Scripture: Or if you do, What are Private Inſtructions of kin to Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquine</hi> puts, in this kinde, the higheſt complement upon Idiots, towards the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his firſt Book <hi>adverſus Gentiles,</hi> by ſinking down the learnedſt to their level. For he teaches us, I remember, to this effect: That the wiſeſt ought not to embrace by Natural Reaſon and Diſcourſe any Article in Religion, were it as manifeſt as that the Whole is bigger then the Part; ſince there may be one ſo ignorant, as to have no notion of what the Whole is, or what the Part. And Religion, that imparts all alike, muſt be grounded (ſays he) upon ſome Principle common and equal to all. Herein the Doctor, I muſt needs ſay, is rightly Angelique: for he walks to me in the clouds. If he mean, by that Principle <hi>Faith,</hi> I underſtand not how that can be ſevered either from Reaſon and Diſcourſe, of which it is the laſt reſult; or from Grace, which is not common. If he mean, by the Principle, that <hi>Tradition of the Church</hi> which you relie on, I know not how that can be an eaſie guidance to the Ignorant, ſince it is ſo difficult a matter to the wiſeſt, to know which is the right Church,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:169831:58"/>whoſe Traditions are ſo ſacred: for unleſs that appear, neither the Ignorant, nor the Wiſe, are like to be much ſatisfied in conſcience, by govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the tenour of their Faith according unto them. If we muſt judge of the Church by <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi>'s Marks, in what miſ-mazes ſhall the Ignorant be guided, whilſt we finde the moſt Knowing involved in ſuch intricacies, in the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of what is meant by Viſibility, Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and Conformity with Antiquity; and to what Society of Chriſtians thoſe attributes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long! If you will have the true Church known by Scripture, which is ſurely the eaſieſt and beſt courſe, (even in the opinion of many learned Papiſts) what is that but to flee back, and make Tradition clear and certain, by that Rule from which you flee, as from what you judge obſcure to Tradition, that you pretend to be evident. And then the Proteſtants will have reaſon to take it heavily, that they ſhould be condemned for founding each part of their Religion upon the ſame ground whereon the Papiſts build all theirs at once: Yea, great reaſon ſhall we have to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it, unleſs a Patent be produced from God Almighty, declaring the Rule of Faith for ſuch a Commodity as may be taken from Scripture in groſs, but not by retail.</p>
               <p>Now that I have anſwered your Objections, I will not be nice in declaring unto you, to the full, my ſence concerning the Sufficiencie and Perſpicuity of Scripture.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:169831:59"/>
               <p>I believe that thoſe Canonical Books which God by his providence hath preſerved unto theſe Times, and which are acknowledged by all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to have been Divinely dictated, do make up a compleat Body of all the material objects of Faith neceſſary to ſalvation; whether explicitely or implicitely neceſſary to be believed.</p>
               <p>I further believe, that in that bleſſed Sacrary there is not onely an incluſive ſufficiencie, to wit, a perfect compriſal of all Saving Doctrines abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely eſſential to Chriſtianity; but an excluſive alſo, that is, ſuch a ſufficiencie as excludes and forbids any Doctrines ſhould be impoſed on Chriſtians for a neceſſary Article of Faith, that is not recorded there. <hi>Nobis curioſitate opus non eſt poſt Chriſtum Jeſum, nec inquiſitione poſt Evangelium, cùm credimus; nihil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideramus ultra credere: hoc enim prius credimus, non eſſe quod ultra credere debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Tert. de prax. adverſ. Haeret. cap. 8.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, I believe that all points whatſoever of Chriſtian Religion are there ſet down as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuouſly, and as clearly intelligible to all capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, as they are clearly neceſſary to be believed by all: And that God's mercy in the merits of Chriſt, accepting alike the Faith reſultant from the dark miſts of the Ignorant, and from the cleareſt intelligence of the Learned,</p>
               <p>The Lamb may wade to his bliſs thorow the ſame water thorow which the Elephant may
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:169831:59"/>ſwim. <hi>Quicquid eſt (mihi crede) in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturis illis altum &amp; divinum eſt, ineſt omnino verit as &amp; reficiendis inſtaur andíſque animis accommodatiſſima diſciplina &amp; plane it a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dificata, ut nemo inde haurire non poſſit quod tibi ſatis eſt, ſi modo ad hauriendum devote &amp; pie, ut vera Religio poſcit, accedat.</hi> Here is the ſaying of <hi>Heraclitus</hi> moſt truely applicable. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Nor truely do I conceive (beſides God's equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing capacities by his own gracious acceptance) that there needs more then a very ordinary one, to underſtand the Scripture in all points abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to ſalvation. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>It may be as well underſtood of the Word of God, as of God the Word, to whom <hi>Clemens (pag.</hi> 56. <hi>adverſ. Gent.</hi>) applies the ſaying. <hi>Magnifice igitur &amp; ſalubriter Spiritus ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus ita Scriptur as ſanctas modificavit, ut locis apertioribus famae occurreret obſcuriori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus autem faſtidia detergeret. Nihil enim fere de illis obſcuritatibus eruitur, quod non planiſſimè dictum alibi reperiatur.</hi> Aug. The great difficulties and obſcurities which are there found, I underſtand chiefly to be in thoſe leſs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial points, wherein mens part-taking ſubtilties
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:169831:60"/>have given to God's Word many various acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions, whilſt not ſeeking the doctrines of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, but thoſe that themſelves are imbued with in it, they uſe it not as the ſtraight and ſtedfaſt Rule to judge of, and avoid Obliquity by, for which it was ordained, but rather as a <hi>Lesbian</hi> Rule, to be bent and deflected according to the ſeveral purpoſes of their own Architecture.</p>
               <p>Verifying of the heavenly food of the ſoul, that fantaſtick imagination of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s heavenly food of the body, Manna, which was ſaid to have been to all differing palats the morſel that each one would have it, and the taſte that his mouth was made to.</p>
               <p>Since then I am thus perſwaded, that God hath lodged within us a Pilot, Reaſon, how weak ſoever, yet proportionate to the Veſſel and the Voyage; and that he hath likewiſe laid open before us a clear and faithful Card, that varies not for any Elevation, Scripture: you muſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me, Couſin, if I chuſe rather to ſteer by that Compaſs thorow the depths of Religion, to our Haven of reſt and beatitude, then like thoſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Navigators that wanted a true Directory, to coaſt it from Doctors to Fathers, from Fathers to Popes, from Popes to Councels, and from all theſe to (but pretended unerring) Tradition. <hi>Quare oportet in care maxime, in qua vitae ratio verſatur, ſibi quemque confidere ſuóque
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:169831:60"/>judicio ac propriis ſenſibus nati ad investi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gandam &amp; perpendendam Veritatem, quàm credentem alienis erroribus decipi, tanquam ipſum Rationis expertem. Dedit omnibus Deus pro virili portione ſapientiam, ut &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>audita inveſtigare poſſent, &amp; audita perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere: nec quia nos illi temporibus anteceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt ſapientia quoque anteceſſerunt, quae ſi omnibus aequaliter datur occupari ab antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus non potest; ſed hoc eos fallit, quod majorum nomine poſito non putant fieri poſſe, &amp; aut ipſi plus ſapiant, quia minores vocan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, aut illi diſſipuerint, quia majores nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantur.</hi> Lactan. Divin. Inſtitut. lib. 1. cap. 8.</p>
               <p>And now (noble Couſin) that I have exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned your Opinions, and diſcuſſed your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, let me have your patience, or your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, a little further, while I give you an account concerning thoſe Directions wherewith you fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour me in your Letter, and in what ſtate I am to follow ſome, and to excuſe my ſelf in others.</p>
               <p>To the firſt, namely, The uſe which you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive we are to make of reading of the Fathers, I willingly conform my ſelf in one part, that is, in letting paſs thoſe things which they write as Divines and Scholars onely, allowing them no more weight with me, then the reaſons wherewith they are accompanied do give them. I am like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe very willing to let paſs, for the moſt part, what they write as Commentors upon the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture;
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:169831:61"/>their interpretations in that kinde being many times (if I may ſo ſay) very Chymerical. Although I muſt tell you, that were I perſwaded of any third Authority by whoſe ſeal the Fathers could tranſmit unto us, in all things of Religion, ſuch certain and unqueſtionable reſolutions as you imagine, I ſhould not expect their aid more earneſtly, nor take the omiſſion more unkindly of them in any thing, then in point of giving us the right and well-handed interpretation of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. I further obey you, in laying hold and relying on what they teach us as Paſtors of the Church; relying (I ſay) upon that chiefly, to wit, in the great Fundamentals of Chriſtianity; but not generally, that is, not in thoſe Queſtions which we diſagree on; wherein they were neither willing nor able to be exact: and leaſt of all, when they inveigh againſt Hereticks; their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and tranſportments being at ſuch times greateſt. As for ſuch Opinions as they deliver Dogmatically, without alleadging texts of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture or learned Arguments to maintain them; although they appear delivered with never ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt an intent, that they ſhould be taken as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith, you muſt pardon me if they ſink no deeper into my belief, then they are driven by ſuch Arguments as my own or others diſcourſe can finde for them, either in Reaſon, Scripture, or Univerſal Tradition.</p>
               <p>Your ſecond advice is, that I ſhould apply my
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:169831:61"/>care to collect thorowout the ſence of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and, by what they ſay, to frame to my ſelf a Model of the Practice, Government, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Church in their times; and then to tell you whether it be like to yours or ours. The Care and Attention you wiſht me, I brought at firſt to the ſtudie of the Fathers: but I cannot brag of the Model I have framed out of them; finding that truely a work hard enough for the beſt Antiquary: And to me 'tis an improvement of the difficulty to an impoſſibility, to be put to tell you which of the preſent Churches hath moſt reſemblance to that of their times: I could as eaſily reſolve you which of two men that ſtood before me, were likeſt to an hundred differing faces. For I do not think there is a greater va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of countenances at a Publike Aſſembly, then there are differences in the ſeveral Ages wherein the Fathers lived, touching thoſe three parts of Religion; eſpecially theſe two, of Practice and Government; of which, <hi>Tertullian,</hi> having ſumm'd up all the chief particulars of the Creed, pronounces, <hi>Hac lege fidei manente, caetera jam diſciplinae &amp; converſationis admittunt novitatem correctionis.</hi> Tert. de Virg. Velan. cap. 1. For matters of Practice, 'tis a clear caſe, what libertie was taken to varie them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſeveral evaſions and ends, ſince ſome of the Apoſtles themſelves, you know, did not ſtick to practiſe Circumciſion: nor do the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:169831:62"/>ſeveral ages appear to me ere a whit the more exquiſite, in the imitation of their fore-fathers, then you will ſay the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is at this day of the Apoſtles in that, and of thoſe that followed after in adminiſtring the Euchariſt to children, and yet 'tis ſhe that pretends to be the Pantomime of antiquitie for matters of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, how <hi>Camelion</hi>-like that hath been, how various, is as viſible as green, and he that would reduce the Church now to the form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the moſt primitive times, ſhould not take in my opinion, the beſt nor wiſeſt courſe, I am ſure not the ſafeſt, for he would be found pecking toward the Presbytery of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which for my part, I beleeve in point of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, hath a greater reſemblance then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yours or ours, to the firſt age of Chriſts Church, and yet is nere a whit the better for it, ſince it was a form not choſen for the beſt, but impoſed by adverſitie and oppreſſion, which in the beginning forc'd the Church from what it wiſht, to what it might, not ſuffering that dignitie and ſtate Eccleſiaſticall, which rightly belong'd unto it, to manifeſt it ſelf to the world; and which ſoon afterwards upon the leaſt <hi>lucida intervalla,</hi> ſhone forth ſo gloriouſly in the happier, as well as more Monarchicall conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Epiſcopacy; of which way of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I am ſo well perſwaded, that I think it pittie 'twas not made betimes, an article of the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:169831:62"/>
                  <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Catechiſm, that Biſhops are <hi>jure divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</hi> But as it is a true maxime in nature, <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptio optimi peſſima,</hi> ſo it holds likewiſe in Government, both civill and Eccleſiaſticall. The beſt of all, Monarchy, feſters oft-times and ſwels into the worſt of all Tyrannie. To which after the firſt 500. years, Policy having or'e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>topt Pietie, the Church made a haſtie progreſs, and of the following ages in this particular, I grant the preſent Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to be a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py farr exceeding the originall, verifying now of the <hi>Roman,</hi> the imputation that <hi>Ariſtides</hi> layd by way of reproach on all other Empires; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. For matters of belief, the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Chriſtians depending chiefly upon them, 'tis true, in the primary and fundamental ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, they have been more conſtant, unanimous, and exact, and in thoſe comparing the Church of their times with yours and ours, I think I may pronounce them all three alike to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but in points leſs material, ſuch as I eſteem thoſe, wherein we two differ, I ſhould contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict my ſelf to undertake the framing out of the Fathers a certain judgement, which of the two preſent Churches were moſt correſpondent to that of their times. Notwithſtanding, if you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand me to ſay for which ſide in my gueſs the Fathers do make moſt, I will tell you truely and freely what I think, holding then the ballance
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:169831:63"/>as even as I can, I conceive the Fathers in ſome few poynts, do lean ſomewhat more to you, as in that of Chriſts deſcent into hell, and alſo in that of free-wil: (thoſe excepted that wrote in heat againſt <hi>Pelagius</hi>) but in other differences, and thoſe of greater importance, I collect, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably, if I am not much deceived, that their ſenſe is much clearer for us, as in the doctrines of Purgatory, and of the Euchariſt, for as touching the firſt, although you may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend in ſome that the words and outward ſhell, wherein the Fathers opinions were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed, belong more to you; yet, if the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be carefully pick'd and examined, I doubt not but the ſenſe and kernel will prove ours; &amp; it will be found that when ever any of the Fathers, <hi>Origen</hi> onely excepted, and his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, who held the very flames of Hell but Purgatory &amp; Temporal; I ſay, thoſe ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, all the expreſſions of the Fathers this way appear clearly to me to have been underſtood, not of a Purgatory, but onely of a probato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fire, whether they meant that of affliction or that of the day of judgement; as for that place in St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> formerly alledged for Purgatory, his beſt commentator <hi>Lod. Vives,</hi> confeſſes he could never meet with it in the ancienter copies of that Fathers admirable works, however crept into the vulgar Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:169831:63"/>
               <p>In point of the Euchariſt, I believe my former inſtances will deſerve a confeſſion of the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lances being ſo equally poyſed in this affaire, as far forth as expreſſion at leaſt, that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbearance of either ſcale is hardly percepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: but did I grant that their words weighed incomparably more on your ſide, yet I ſhould not doubt to challenge their ſenſe for us, and that moſt confidently upon this reaſon; That ſuppoſing the Fathers to have believed as we doe, the Sacrament to be Bread, great reaſon might they have notwithſtanding, to raiſe the majeſty of it in their expreſſions, and to term it the body of Chriſt, it being uſuall, and thought neceſſary in the primitive times to wrap up the Sacraments of the Church in myſteries, that the Catechumens might be poſſeſt with a more awfull reverence towards them, and be whetted and fan'd as it were to a more keen and ardent deſire of being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto them; eſpecially the danger be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much more eaſie for them to think too meanly of what bore the name of Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but was palpably bread, then that they ſhould fall to adore that for God, which their eare onely told them was the fleſh of Chriſt, and all their other ſenſes aſſured them to be the commoneſt food of mankind; wheras ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them to have believed as the Church
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:169831:64"/>of <hi>Rome</hi> doth, that the Sacrament is the very Fleſh and blood of our Saviour, and to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with the ſame reverence that belongs to God himſelfe, there can be no warrantable reaſon why they ſhould at any time leſſen the majeſty of ſo ſacred an object of our adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or give it ſo often the name of thoſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary elements, whoſe evidence to our ſenſe ſhould they alwayes have ſaid all they could invent, of dignifying, would ſtill have been apt enough to give an allay to the faith and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration that's pretended to.</p>
               <p>Theſe being as I conceive, two of the moſt important Articles of difference between your Church and ours, what hath been ſaid will ſuffice to manifeſt unto you, that throughout this diſcourſe I decline not the trial by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers out of any diſtruſt of our cauſe: for tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly though I will not allow their, Writings to be the proper tribunall at which our contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies are to be judged, I ſhould be content to referre with you the whole matter to their arbitration, and voluntarily to allow them that determinating power which in right they cannot claim; ſo farre am I from acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging a greater conformity in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> then in ours to what they teach, to have been either the Government, Practice, or Beliefe of the primitive times, nor yet ſhould I refuſe them for Arbitrators as perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:169831:64"/>as I doe for Judges, I would not think my pains loſt, or ſtudy of the Fathers not worth the while: For beſides the addition of knowledge and general improvement of the Soul, which one muſt be a very ſtupid Reader of the Fathers, not to advance in, by the helps of their great and univerſal learning, beſides the admirable excitations to piety and zeale; I conceive that even in the affair of directing us to a ſoul-ſaving Religion, a Chriſtian by ſearching into their ancient me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials may as you ſay, reap a far greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, then either Criticks or Lawyers do in their ſeveral Sciences from their worm-ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten monuments of Antiquity; for they, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, from thoſe maymed evidences of broken and disjoynted Records, draw out principles; it is true, ſo probable, as may prudentially in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a rational and equal Surveyers aſſent, from which they frame perhaps ſome ſuch text, whereby indifferent men, do conſent to be regulated; but we by our holy ſearch into the Sacraries of former ages are led to a text already divinely framed; A text perfectly comprizing all parts requiſite to the ſupreme Science it concerns; A text whoſe very affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is an uncontroulable reſolution; from our Records of antiquity, wee draw not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Topical Arguments, but proofs to any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing man above demonſtration; ſuch as
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:169831:65"/>it were madneſs and impiety to reject upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny argument to the contrary; and this in all points of Religion, miſtake me not, I mean that do really and confeſtly on all hands im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port Heaven or Hell in mens beliefs and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe: and from hence, though I ſhould deny the Fathers any uſefulneſs at all in our contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, yet, I ſhould extreamly gratulate to my ſelf the labour and ambition to be in ſome good meaſure skill'd in their Antiquities, and to you your great and (according to your principles) moſt judicious progreſs in them.</p>
               <p>Your next advice is, that I ſhould apply my underſtanding and induſtry to build up as well as to pull down, and to examine as ſtrictly the reaſons of my own belief, to ſee whether that be wel grounded; as thoſe for the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opinion, to obſerve whether that be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly demonſtrated; I muſt confeſs, I ever thought it a ſuperfluous labour, to ſeek to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh one part of a contradiction, by any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proof then the deſtruction of the other; and you your ſelf ſuppoſing our Tenents con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory, do warrant that for a truth, (to me) ſufficiently proved, and preſs on me a neceſſity of imbracing whatſoever is contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory to a falſhood.</p>
               <p>'Tis true that St <hi>Jerome</hi> paſſes upon <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius,</hi> a cenſure in a wiſh; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam tam
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:169831:65"/>noſtra confirmare putuiſſit quam facile alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na diſtruxit;</hi> but his caſe and ours are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, 'twas not ſo convincing an Argument; <hi>Paganiſm</hi> is ridiculous, <hi>Judaiſm</hi> exolete; Therefore Chriſtians are in every thing in the right, as 'tis with us, the Church and tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not infallible in all things, therefore fallible in ſome; the bread is not tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated, therefore it remains bread. There is no third place for us after death, beſides hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and hell, and no fall from the one, and no redemption from the other, therefore no Purgatorie; In theſe and the like caſes, one partie is ſure and firm ſetled when ever the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falls, as certainly as in natural generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the decay of one thing is infallibly the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of another: And therefore in point of wrong and unfitting ſuperſtructures, ſuch as moſt of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Tenents are, which we lay battery to, it may ſuffice to pull down, thoſe being demoliſht, what's rightly built will ſtand faſt of it ſelf, ſince both ſuppoſe a foundation.</p>
               <p>Now for the ſecond part of your direction, namely, that I ſhould ſtrictly examin the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my own belief, I have obeyed you to the full; And that you may be able to judg whether they be well weighed or no, take here a ſum of my belief; I believe the unity and Omnipotence of God, and an inexplicable Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:169831:66"/>in that unity; I beleeve the incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſecond perſon of that Trinity, that's Gods aſſumption of perfect humanity from the womb of a Virgin; And that he humbled himſelf, not onely to manhood, but alſo to mortallity; that after he had ſet our practice an exact pattern by his life, and by his words imbued our Theory with all neceſſary docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he might purge our ſtaines with his blood, redeem our forfeitures by the price of his paſſion, and preſent a plenary ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his Fathers Juſtice for all our miſdeeds; I beleeve further, that to make us capable of the effects of his merits, Beatitude, he illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates our underſtanding by the gift of the holy Ghoſt, by whom is created in us that divine faith, by which theſe miſteries are to be apprehended: I beleeve alſo, that our bleſſed Saviour gave his Apoſtles commiſſion to preach to all the world his ſaving Doctrine, who did accordingly, and have left to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, both written records, and living ones in ſucceſſions of the faithfull, that ſhall preſerve even to the end of the world, theſe and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther articles neceſſary to ſalvation. I like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe beleeve that the Apoſtles eſtabliſhed Paſtors in ſeveral Churches, whom we are to hearken unto with reverence, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of them the Sacraments of regeneration to Chriſt, and of Communion with him, both
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:169831:66"/>which by Gods grace, have a divine and ſupernatural effect in the cleanſing us from ſin; I beleeve that heaven ſhall be the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the good, and hell of the wicked: and laſtly in a word (to ſupply whatſoever may have been omitted) I firmly beleeve whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is evidently contained in the Creed or Scripture, or clearly deduceable from either. I am perſwaded that you will yeild that the reaſons upon which theſe are built, will abide the ſtricteſt examination. None of theſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions I hope betrayeth its own weakneſs? And yet theſe are the only opinions which I have been imbued with, theſe are the parts of faith that integrate my Religion, in theſe are compriſed al points that I think neceſſary to be believed; And he that believes any thing more, if he have but his ſhare of good works, is ſafe in my opinion, for he hath faith of ſupererrogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; my firm and reſolute ſettlement in theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, defends me from being at all concerned in thoſe ſeverall imputations which towards the cloſe of your letter you do moſt judiciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and juſtly lay upon Sciolous and Sapticall witts, that floating in uncertainty, would fain reduce every thing to that paſs, ſeeking ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to puzle and imbroil an adverſary, then weightily to eſtabliſh a ſolid truth. 'Tis that ſolid truth, and ſuch as bears no diſpute, that I wiſh we might all ſtick to; and let paſs thoſe
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:169831:67"/>quillets, and niceties impoſed by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for Articles of importance, and which her adherents dwell upon with too ſcrupulous a diligence; ſuch as admit arguments on both ſides, and are fitter for a declamation then a Catechiſm, in which whilſt men vainly buſie themſelves, they let ſlide away many times unnoted, as you ſay, that great deal which is uncontroulable and plain points, which can be thought at beſt but at the skirts, none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the main body of religion; doctrines for the moſt part (at the leaſt in my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) ſo little material; that I applaud the Fathers for ſpending ſo little time or labour on them; ſuch, as I am ſo far from delighting to make objections in, that where ever I have touch'd upon particulars, it hath been a <hi>Contre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coeur,</hi> and onely to diſperſe ſuch duſt as others raiſe; for I ſwear there is no man living hath a ſtronger averſion then my ſelf from all cavils in Religion; it being juſtly to be feared, as our great Prelate (Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Cant.</hi> in his Epiſtle to his Majeſtie) ſayes, that Atheiſm and irreligion gathers ſtrength, while the truth is thus weakned by an unworthy way of contending for it; and I am perſwaded that mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> men, while their thoughts are ſo buſied in <hi>chicanes</hi> of controverted points, grow ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligent of thoſe more weighty ones that neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyer import ſalvation, and ſo runne out of the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:169831:67"/>moſt eſſentiall good of their ſoules, as imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently as many a peeviſh freeholder that waſts a ſolid eſtate, in endleſs law ſuits for a trifle; &amp; as I think theſe points little important for uſe, ſo I concur with you in eſteeming both theſe, and all other matters of Religion very unfit to be argued on for oſtentation or applauſe, which I am ſure I am as farr from aiming at in this ſubject, as I ſhall be farr from attaining it. 'Tis true, the condition of the knowing &amp; ignorant, is uſually quite contrary to the Lords ſervants in the Goſpel, there he that had leaſt, wrapt up his ſingle talent in a Napkin; but amongſt men now a-daies that pretend, whoever hath leaſt, it is he longs moſt to ſhew how much he hath, and ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhes how little; yet, thus far they oftentimes both agree, that neither improve their ſtore: and thus by my ignorance unleſs you be chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, I confeſs my ſelf liable to be ſuſpected guilty of the vain appetite of oftentation that uſually accompanies it; but as my Ignorance expoſes me to the ſuſpition, ſo my conſciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it (the ſole knowledge that I can brag of) frees me from the Ambition ſuſpected, and layes upon me a neceſſity of concluding with a huge Apologie, for preſuming to give you ſo much trouble, and, I fear, ſo little ſatisfaction: I confeſs I ought to have been reſtrained from venturing at all upon this
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:169831:68"/>Debate, the Subject it ſelf being ſo farr above the pitch of my literature; And the Perſon with whom I preſume to argue the difference of Opinion, confeſtly my ſuperiour in all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages both of Nature and Acquiſition, beyond all hopes of compariſon; Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions either of them able to deterr a much conſidenter man then my ſelf: But Friendſhip, which always findes, or makes men equall, hath long ſince licenc't me from the latter, and hardened me to impart my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, how low ſo ever, as freely to you, as I could doe to any inferiour Wit of mine own levell: And for the firſt, I have neglected it upon this perſwaſion, that I ſhall be better able to anſwer to the Divines, a young, a Lay, and ignorant mans adventuring to treat of their Buſineſs, then to you, and to my ſelf ſo womaniſh a wrong, as not ſubſcription to the Dictamens of your ſtrong and powerfull Soul, without yeelding my reaſons for the variance, which how light ſoever they may be found, when pondered by your excellent judgment, yet being really ſuch, as are moſt convincing to mine, they will ſerve to excuſe me to you, to juſtifie me to my ſelf, and I hope to make my Errours even pardonable with God, who when by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> he bids us be <hi>able to give a Reaſon of the hope that is in us;</hi> I am confident he expects it no better
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:169831:68"/>then proportionable to the capacities that his goodneſs hath endowed us with: Anſwerable to them is this Diſcourſe, weak I confeſs, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynted, and without Nerves; and yet I doubt not but it may be ſo evictuated by Truth and the goodneſs of my Cauſe, that I ſhall not be aſhamed to have encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred a <hi>GOLIAH</hi> with a Sling. A Straw kept in a right Line, might batter a tower; from which right line of truth and reaſon, I may ſafely proteſt I have not ſo much as once voluntary ſwarved in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, through any partaking paſſion, or forelaid deſigne, neither have I ſuffered my ſelf; herein to be ſo far wrought upon by civility, as to forbear a free and round expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my ſenſe, where ever it differed from yours: and truly, there was no cauſe why I ſhould, ſince in our diſputes, the ſtrongeſt oppoſition, that I or the beſt wit for me can poſſibly make to your opinions, will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate no more from your unqueſtionable exellency of judgement, then it would conclude either of us ill-ſighted ſhould you affirm ſuch a Garment to be red, and I that it were green, the object being a change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Taffaty, and we ſeated in contrary lights, or looking through mediums diverſly tincted; a like affect upon the ſoul, to theſe upon the ſenſe, hath diverſity of education, and
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:169831:69"/>diſcrepance of thoſe principles wherewith men are at the firſt imbued, and whereon all our after reaſonings are founded: Conformity and uniteneſs of minde, as rarely flowing from contrary Educations, as the ſame River from oppoſite ſprings; ſweet, happy, and I think ſole, is the ſelf-ſameneſs which ariſes from pure principles of nature, never ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticated by the artifices of our breeding, but little derivation from thoſe Fountaines hath this or that Sect of Religion, &amp; ſo no marvel if we agree not therin to be one, as we do in the other moſt true &amp; prime Emanation of nature, Friendſhip; which, on your part to me I am confident muſt needs ſpring from thence, ſince my ſmall merit affords no other motive; and for mine to you, I am ſure it is impoſſible without an intire concurrence of all the forces of Sympathy, for any man to reverence, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, and love another, with that Ardour as I do you deareſt Couſin, and which you cannot but own in</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>SHERBORN,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>March</hi> 30. 1639.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your moſt faithful and moſt Affectionate Servant. G. D.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:169831:69"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
